<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second sound, or vvarning of the trumpet vnto judgement Wherein is proued, that all the tokens of the latter day, are not onelie come, but welneere finished. With an earnest exhortation, to be in continuall readinesse. By Anthonie Marten sewer of her Maiesties most honorable chamber.</title>
            <author>Marten, Anthony, d. 1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 133 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107009</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842714</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842714</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7396</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 479:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second sound, or vvarning of the trumpet vnto judgement Wherein is proued, that all the tokens of the latter day, are not onelie come, but welneere finished. With an earnest exhortation, to be in continuall readinesse. By Anthonie Marten sewer of her Maiesties most honorable chamber.</title>
                  <author>Marten, Anthony, d. 1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 40 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin, for Andrew Maunsell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The second warning vnto iudgement.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Second Advent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A ſecond Sound, or Warning of the Trumpet vnto Judgement.</p>
            <p>Wherein is proued, that all the tokens of the Latter day, are not onelie come, but welneere finiſhed.</p>
            <p>With an earneſt Exhortation, to be in continuall readineſſe.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthonie Marten</hi> Sewer of her Maieſties moſt honorable Chamber.</p>
            <q>
               <p>When ye ſee theſe things come to paſſe, be ye ſure that he is euen at the doores.</p>
               <bibl>Mark. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>PRO LEGE ET GREGE</q>
               <q>LOVE KEPYTHE LAWE, OBEYETH THE KYNGE, AND IS GOOD TO THE COMMEN WELTHE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for Andrew Maunſell. 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>oſt renowmed and mightie Prince, Jt pleaſeth your highnes, after a long win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters abode in ſome one of your Princely Pallaces, (the ſtormes of colde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing past, and the pleaſant ſpring tide come) to remooue your houſeholde into a freſh and wholſome aire. And for a warning to your officers, and ſeruaunts of your Court, you doe cauſe the Trumpet to bee three ſeuerall times ſounded, against you deſcende from the higher part of your manſion. But if it happen to bee long before the ſeconde warning of the trumpet be giuen, the third is no ſooner ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but your owne Perſon is then comming. Then must all your ſeruants be readie to waite
<pb facs="tcp:7396:3"/>vpon you: you are the Souereigne, and not to expect for anie. They that be not readie at the ſame inſtant, are not worthie of ſuch a Prince, nor to haue reward for ſuch a ſeruice. Euen ſo the most inuincible King of glorie Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who by his holie ſpirit, hath been preſent in this worldly manſion, with his houſhold the Church welneere 1600. yeares while it hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden many ſharpe and bitter ſtormes, &amp; hath been as it were impriſoned within the Pallace of this wretched world, is now minded ſpeedely to remooue the ſame into his owne Countrie, a pleaſand land, and place of felicitie. The first warning of his remooue, he ſounded by his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when his fame was ſpread ouer all the world, by the first preaching of the Goſpel. The ſecond he hath proclaimed by the preachers of his word, whom he reuiued (as it were) out of the dust, within theſe 70. yeres. And together with them, are ſent all the promiſed tokens of his comming. Howbeit the day being ſo farre ſpent, before his ſeconde warning, wee ſhall ſee himſelfe ſpeedely deſcend from aboue with the
<pb facs="tcp:7396:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>third ſound of the trumpet, and in the voyce of an Archangel. And thoſe that watch for him with their lampes burning, he will receiue, and the rest he will exclude from his kingdom, &amp; from the reward of his ſeruice. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>herfore your Highnes, beeing one of his principall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, nay, at this day the chiefe Stewarde of his houſehold, it ſhall be a perpetuall honour to your kingdome, a not able bleſſing to your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, an vnſpeakable benefit to the Church, an acceptable ſeruice to Christ, yea an eternal fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie to your ſelf, if the light of your lampe do continuallie ſhine, and the oyle of your workes doe perpetually abound, that nowe at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ye may bee readie to enter with him into that glorie which he hath promiſed to all thoſe which be faithfull ſeruants.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt humble Subiect, and Seruant:</hi> Anthonie Marten.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7396:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſecond Sound or warning</hi> of the Trumpet vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ften &amp; ſundrie times did God foreſhew vnto our forefathers in the olde Teſtament, the firſt comming of his Son into this world, &amp; the taking of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon him moſt plainly &amp; euidently did he declare vnto them, that Chriſt by his death ſhould reſtore vs vnto life, and that by his reſurrection and aſcenſion, hee ſhould make perfect the worke of our ſaluation. In like manner did hee with no leſſe perſpicuitie ſet foorth vnto them, the returne of our Sauiour vnto iudgement, and that all men ſhould riſe againe vnto immortalitie, and render an account of all their workes and actions. All this did hee promiſe them by his Prophetes, iuſtifie in his perſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme firme by manie maruellous ſignes and wonders: ſuch as were neuer heard of before ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. Yet did the obſtinate Iewes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den their hearts and beleeued not. Wherefore God made them no more nation, but ſcattered them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all lands, in ſuch wiſe wee ſee them at this day to be a ſcorne and deriſion vnto all people.</p>
            <p>Neither can the example of theſe men ſo often rebuked by vs for their incredulitie, ſo greatly bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for their obſtinacie, ſo ſharply reprooued by vs
<pb facs="tcp:7396:5"/>for their crueltie, ſo iuſtlie deſpiſed for their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie, any thing amend vs in the ſame things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee condemne them. For what promiſe haue they, and wee haue it not performed? What Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie had they, and we haue it not fulfilled? What true Religion had they, and we haue it not reſtored? What worde, what teſtimonie, what ſignes, what miracles, what mercies, what graces, and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites had they, and we haue them not a thouſand times more increaſed. Yet are we altogether either incredulous of the promiſes, or doubtful of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, or elſe careleſſe and deſperate of our own deliueraunce. And this maketh vs to leane to the fables and deceaueable doctrines of men, more then to the true Propheſies of the word of God, &amp; to the commandements of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who haue declared the ſecond comming of Chriſt, and that in ſuch plaine and euident ſort, as they haue ſhewed the verie time when, the manner how, and the things themſelues that ſhoulde withholde: the ſignes and tokens that ſhould goe before, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther certainties whatſoeuer are neceſſarie for man to knowe, as concerning the ſame. And by this meanes, if the iudgement of God and finall deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world do come ſodainely vpon man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be aware, there is no ignoraunce to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, there is no excuſe to bee regarded, there is no darkeneſſe of the Scriptures to be alledged. For it al the holie Bible, there is not anie one thing that the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7396:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>mercie and goodneſſe of our God hath ſet downe more amplie, taught more plainlie, and ſet foorth more expreſlie, for the aſſurance of our faith, than the tokens of Chriſts comming.</p>
            <p>And as the preaching and publiſhing of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by the Apoſtles, miniſters and diſciples of Chriſt, in the firſt ages after his aſcenſion, was the firſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Trumpet, ſounded at that time vnto all Nations againſt the reſurrection of the fleſh, and of Chriſts returne againe vnto iudgement: ſo the reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Goſpel, and reuealing of Antichriſt by preaching of the worde; together with the other ſignes &amp; tokens that Chriſt himſelfe told vs ſhould come to paſſe before his ſecond comming, is a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorie warning that ſhall be giuen vnto all fleſh. For the laſt ſound of the Trumpet, ſhall bee no more properlie a warning, but an haſtie and ſodaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, a crying vnto iudgement, and appearing of Chriſt in the cloudes, a periſhing of the heauens, &amp; a conſuming of the earth and all the workes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with fire.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I meane heere to put the Chriſtian world in minde of all thoſe tokens, as neere as I can by that order, which Chriſt himſelfe and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles wel neere 1600. yeeres paſt haue declared in the word of God. And therein I will examine how manie of thoſe ſignes and tokens be paſt, and howe manie of them doe yet remaine to be fulfilled. Then will I ſee, whither this bee not the verie time that
<pb facs="tcp:7396:6"/>Chriſt hath preſcribed to returne againe: or if the time be not yet full complete, whither it bee not ſo verie neere therevnto, as it is moſt certaine that the ſame ſhall not be long deferred. Laſtlie, I will do my beſt to ſtirre vp the mindes of all men to repentance, and to prepare themſelues with all the diligence &amp; duetie they can ſhewe in this life, to go foorth of meete with that great Prince of glorie Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Albeit our forefathers in euerie age ſince the time of the Apoſtles, had manie ſignes and tokens, whereby euerie one might looke for the day of the Lord in that age werein he liued; and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid in his time, that the examples of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wer writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a warning vnto vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ends of the world were come;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10, 11,</note> yet becauſe the perceiued by the wordes of Chriſt, that there were other tokens to be performed, which neither they had ſeene, nor yet did wel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue, they might not ſo boldlie preſcribe the day of the Lord to be at hand, as we may now affirme it to be. For although Saint <hi>Paule</hi> (as I haue ſhewed) did ſay that the ends of the worlde were come vpon them in his dayes, yet lie bad the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> that they ſhould not bee deceaued by anie ſpirit, or word, or letter, to thinke that the day of the Lord was then at hand.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.2.</note> For hee taught them that there ſhould be firſt a falling away from the faith: and that Antichriſt ſhould be reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before the comming of Chriſt. Which things were not to bee performed within the compaſſe of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7396:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo fewe yeeres, but required a longer time, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other matters depended thereon. Now how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this propheſie of Antichriſt may ſeeme to take a latter place in the holie Hiſtorie after ſome other ſignes and tokens of Chriſts comming, yet if we haue regarde to the firſt times when the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was declared to bee that Antichriſt, it may take the firſt place before al other ſignes, accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed after Chriſt his aſcenſion. Neuertheleſſe if we meane ſo plaine &amp; perfect a reuealing of Antichriſt, as it ſhall be no leſſe euident vnto al other nations of Chriſtendome, than it is now vnto vs, who doe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſee &amp; perfectly know him to be the verie man of ſinne which was propheſied before (whereunto the holie Ghoſt had reſpect, in putting this ſigne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter others in the place of <hi>Mathew, Marke</hi> and elſe where) then may it be called the laſt ſigne or token of all. Becauſe, as the publiſhing of the worde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the world, groweth by little and little, ſo the perfect reuealing of Antichriſt vnto all Nations, is daily more and more plainely and euidently diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby. And in this reſpect, the preaching of the word with the conſuming of him ſhall end both together, at the verie comming of Chriſt, and not before: becauſe the Scripture ſaith, that the ſpirit of the Lords mouth ſhall conſume him, but the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his comming ſhall vtterly deſtroy him.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.8.</note> And both this, and the reſt of the tokens that depende on the ſame, are moſt euident and vndoubted teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb facs="tcp:7396:7"/>of the latter dav. Wherefore I will firſt ſhew how all thoſe thinges are performed partly in other time before, but moſt eſpecially in this age of ours. Within which time alſo I will declare all the reſt of the tokens of Chriſt comming to be in a manner fully complete.</p>
            <p>When the kingdome of Chriſt was increaſed, and growen to the full by preaching of the Goſpel, and that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> began alſo to growe great in <hi>Italy,</hi> by decaying of the Empire, &amp; by the giftes and donacions of Princes, then did alſo the ſame Biſhop fall from true religion to ſuperſtition; from the right ſeruice of God, to falſe worſhipping; from ſinceritie, to hypocriſie; from the rules of Gods word, to the reaſons &amp; decrees of men. And as his greatneſſe increaſed, &amp; the Emperours power diminiſhed, ſo the Apoſtaſie of that Church was the more diſcerned, &amp; Antichriſt of <hi>Rome</hi> the more reuealed: and ſo when <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſeate of the Empire was vtterly remoued from the temporal Magiſtrate, and wholly inueſted in the Pope, and that the Pope claimed to be the vniuerſall Biſhop, there was now nothing to hinder, but that all men might diſcerne how farre the Church was falne from God, &amp; who was very Antichriſt the Author of the ſame. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, though he by this meanes ſhewed himſelf to be that Antichriſt, which both the Prophetes and alſo Chriſt and his Apoſtles had ſo manifeſtly deſcribed before hand, as there can be nothing in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7396:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>more plaine, yet can it not be ſaide, that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was fully reuealed, till this latter age of ours; both becauſe the infinite meaſure of his iniquitie was neuer before fulfilled, with ſo great power and ſignes and lying wonders, as it hath bene now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few ages paſt: and alſo becauſe hee made princes his miniſters and vaſſals, to ſee that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements were obſerued, and his honour, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and power maintained; and that none ſhoulde be ſo hardie as to bring his name in queſtion, or to finde fault with anie part of his ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>But when it pleaſed God of his infinite mercie to put into the hearts of Kings and Princes, prudently to ſnake off his intollerable yoke from their ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and to ſend foorth preachers of his word, that ſhoulde openly pronounce him to bee verie Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and to proue it to his face out of the worde of God, that he is that man of ſinne foreſhewed in the Scripture, then it might truly be ſaid, that there was no impediment betweene him and home, but that he is perfectly, infallibly, and expreſly diſcouered, taught &amp; knowen to be Antichriſt among all them that profeſſe the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, the matter being ſo true, as both the word of God it ſelfe affirmeth, and the teſtimonies and proofes of innumerable Writers extant inuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth, I need not wade anie further here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, than is neceſſarie to induce the matter I haue in hand For this beeing true, that the Apoſtacie of
<pb facs="tcp:7396:8"/>that Church drawing to an ende by preaching of of the word; that all the impediments, which kept Antichriſt backe, that he could not be ſo manifeſt to the world being remoued; that Antichriſt himſelf is now in this age of ours moſt euidently diſcyphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that thoſe be the principall and moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſignes of he Lords comming, whereof the reſt or manie of them depend, and might not be ſhewed till theſe were fulfilled; we are now to ſee what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tokens the holy Ghoſt hath ſet downe in the word written, that ſhould be ſhewed a little before the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, that before the end of the world <hi>Nation ſhall riſe againſt nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 24. Mark. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and Realme againſt Realme, and there ſhall be famines, and pestilence, and earthquakes in certaine places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Antichriſt hath long and quietly helde the poſſeſsion both of the temporall and ſpirituall ſwordes, when hee hath manie yeeres taken vpon him the office of Chriſt, to be the King of Kinges and Lord of Lords, and to haue the domimon aſwel of the ſoules as of the bodies of men, it is great &amp; horrible griefe vnto him to looſe ſo high a domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſtoope from the office of God which hee taketh vpon him, among men, to become as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man: &amp; therefore he deuiſeth by all meanes to puniſh and diſquiet the Saints of God. Whom he may bring into his power, them he vexeth, them he tormenteth, them he burneth, them hee deſtroyeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7396:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>without all pitie or mercie. And if they be ſuch as for their authoritie and greatneſſe he cannot, or by reaſon of the protection of others he dare not bring vnder his tyrannie, he ſtirreth vp Kings and Princes of his confederacie, to make warres vpon them. Or if that faile, he moueth their owne ſubiects to rebel and put themſelues in armes againſt them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee hath at this day ſet in an vprore the whole Chriſtian world; kingdome againſt kingdome, and nation againſt nation, &amp; one people againſt another, that he may the eaſier (as hee thinketh) defende his proud and inſolent gouernment, his falſe and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious religion, and the ſeate and dignitie of his Popedome. Neither can that place of Scripture of <hi>Nation riſing against Nation, and kingdome againſt king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> be more neceſſarilie vnderſtood of anie other warres to be made between Prince &amp; Prince, than ſuch as Antichriſt raiſeth vp for religion ſake. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I euer heare of anie warres before this age of ours between the nations &amp; kingdoms of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome for Chriſt his cauſe: that is to ſay, for the true worſhipping of him, for the preaching of his Goſpel, for the difference in opinions, for the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the conſcience, and for the triall of the true Church: and that ſo earneſtlie and continuallie and without hope of reconciliation; till now that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt for the ſauing of his dominion, hath made all theſe commotions and troubles in the world, which cannot bee decided till Chriſt in his owne perſon
<pb facs="tcp:7396:9"/>come to trie his own cauſe in iudgement. But for all other temporall cauſes the Nations and Princes of Chriſtendome haue one riſen againſt another euer ſince the time that Chriſt aſcended vp into heauen.</p>
            <p>Wherefore this is the ſenſe &amp; meaning of theſe words of Chriſt: Towards the ende of the worlde when Antichriſt is reuealed, and that he feareth to forgo his Crowne and dominion, hee ſhall ſtirre vp the Princes that be his Confederates to warre vpon the Nations and Cities that profeſſe the Goſpel, that what he is not able to doe of his owne power, nor by his falſe and forged miracles, nor by gathering of his general Councels, nor by pronouncing of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications and curſes, nor by the wrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of the Scriptures, nor by the writings and diſputations of his ſchoole Doctors, nor by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroad of his Seminarie prieſts and hypocrites, that wil he endeuor to do by the help of other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vnder pretence of doing God good ſeruice. And this notable token foretolde of Chriſt as touching his ſecond comming, we ſee is alreadie at hand, and is like euerie day more and more to bee verified to the great effuſion of Chriſtian bloud.</p>
            <p>In like manner, as concerning famine peſtilences and earthquakes, foreſhewed by Chriſt in the ſecond place, they are not ſo fitlie to bee referred to anie of thoſe which houe ben in times paſt, before this man of ſinne was reuealed. For thoſe haue been heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore manie, great and horrible, yee and at ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7396:9"/>in ſome places almoſt vniuerfall. But thoſe which haue happened, and ſhall happen in our time, when Antichriſt ſhalbe more and more reuealed, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition abandoned, the power of the beaſt decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the kingdome of Chriſt reuiued, the Goſpel free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie publiſhed, and the ſecond warning of the trumpet ſounded, thoſe be vndoubted teſtimonies and tokens that the day of the Lord is at hand. Such haue were now had within the compaſſe of theſe few yeeres, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen manie, and great, and horrible: ſomtimes in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Cities and Countries, and ſometime in whole Prouinces of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>What wonderfull famines haue we had in places diſtreſſed &amp; beſieged by the champions of Antichriſt, both in Fraunce, the Low Countries, and other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prouinces; not ſent immediately by the finger of God, but conſtrained for the moſt part by the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of Antichriſt: by whoſe meanes it is to be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that beyond the horror of all famines that euer I heard of, or read, men haue been conſtrained to pull out the dead carkaſes buried in graues, to make ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for their bodies.</p>
            <p>Peſtilences alſo there haue been manie and great, beſides thoſe former ſignes and tokens: In <hi>England;</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; welneere in euerie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>We our ſelues alſo haue lately heard and felt great and fearefull earthquakes, to put vs in minde of the promiſe of Chriſt, and therefore to aſſure our ſelues of his ſpeedie comming vnto iudgement, leaſt if we
<pb facs="tcp:7396:10"/>prouide not for the ſame, we be ſodeinly taken tardie, and for our wickednes be caſt into the lake of fire and brimſtone, that neuer ſhalbe quenched.</p>
            <p>In the third place is ſhewed, what anguiſh &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Saints of God ſhall endure for Chriſtes ſake; eſpecially when they haue made it manifeſt to all the world, that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is that ſonne of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which exalteth himſelf aboue God. For then doth he ſeek by all maner of meanes to kil &amp; deſtroy them: by impriſonment, by torment, by fire, by ſworde, by poyſon, by laying in waite, by treaſon, by charging them with hereſie, by taking away their good name, and by cauſing them to bee hated of all people: euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more imagining with himſelfe, that by theſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hee ſhall ſo waſt and deſtroy them, that at the length the remembrance of them ſhall be cleerely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct from the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>Howbeit the more blood he ſpilleth, the more the Church of God increaſeth; and the longer thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to put off the day of iudgement, the ſooner ſhall it be haſtened for the choſen ſake, and for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the wicked worlde, and of him in the midſt thereof.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when the worlde ſhall perceiue ſo great troubles to ariſe by preaching of the Goſpel, and that no temporall benefite commeth thereby; that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth kingdomes to bee at warres one againſt another, that there be as great or greater famines, plagues, and earthquakes as euer, that iniquitie aboundeth more that euer, that the loue of men &amp; faith towards God,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7396:10"/>is leſſe than euer, that Gods diſpleaſure is more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous than euer. Finally that the Pope for all the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching againſt him, can no more be remoued out of his ſeate than euer: the vngodly ſeede of Antichriſt are ſo offended therewith, as they betray into wicked hands their owne countrimen, their kinred and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, yea they hate their own brethren, &amp; ſeek their deſtruction. And this did Chriſt foreſhewe to happen in the ende of the world.</p>
            <p>Fiftly he declared, that at the ſame time manie falſe Prophetes ſhould ariſe and deceiue a multitude. For when Antichriſt perceiued, that he might not preuaile by anie of thoſe vile and violent meanes that hee had practized, but that his power neuertheleſſe decreaſed, and his al hominable ſuperſtition and idolatrie was daily more and more diſcloſed, he erected certein Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie places for learning, with good maintenaunce to the ſame, for all thoſe that would reſort vnto them of all nations, to the ende they might bee ſent home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, after they haue been certeine yeres ripened and rottened in ſuperſtitious doctrine, that by their fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hypocriſie, and by their falſe fables and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, they might reconcile all thoſe that were fled from the Antichriſtian faith, promiſing them ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and ſo great matters, as their holy Father by his Commiſsion had giuen them in charge: And theſe miniſters of his be they which <hi>Paule</hi> the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>To haue the forme of godlineſse, but denie the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:</hi> &amp; haue by their falſe propheſies,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.</note> caried away ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie poore ſoules captiue into hell, and themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:7396:11"/>alſo are damned for euer without repentaunce. And this token of the Lordes comming is nowe likewiſe fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Againe Chriſt hath declared, that before the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment day, iniquitie ſhall abound, and the loue of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſhall wexe colde.</p>
            <p>But what kinde of iniquitie do we think ſhal abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d before the ſecond coming of Chriſt? Verelie al kinde of ſine and wickedneſſe, that euer was in the world ſince the creation of the ſame, not onely the ſecrete ſinnes that proceede from mans heart, whereby the whole man is corrupted, but the publike offences and enormities done by man againſt man, againſt God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church, againſt the Common weale, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all iuſtice, godlineſſe and Religion. And is it anie maruell, why all wickedneſſe ſhoulde abounde now towards the ende, more than euer before? why the charitie of man towardes man, why the loue of man towardes God, why the zeale of man towardes godlineſſe, ſhould now bee leſſe than before? though now the word of God be more plentifullie preached that before; the ſacraments more ſincerely miniſtred than before hereſies &amp; falſe worſhipping more ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie conuinced than before: the true Church from the falſe more euidently diſcerned than before, Antichriſt himſelfe more plainly detected than before; and our ſaluation now more neere at hand than before? No verely. For now is the time that Chriſt preſcribed, &amp; neuer before. Now is Sathan our olde enimie looſed, now it Antichriſt his ſeruant reuealed.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:7396:11"/>
            <p>For euer ſince the time that the kingdome of Chriſt hath been reuiued by preaching of the Goſpell, the Dragon hauing the time of his thouſand yeeres capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie welneere expired, and perceiuing his dominion to be but ſhort, is come foorth to aide and ſtrengthen, and heale the wound of the beaſt, againſt the Saintes of God, and againſt the Lambe. Who ioyning their forces together, ſeeke by their craftie and lying hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, not onely to bereaue men of their ſaluation, by deceiuing and bewitching of their ſoules, and by dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them forwarde to all manner of ſinne and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, but alſo to deſtroy their bodies and all, by bringing in vpon them all manner of cruel Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, warres, torments, miſeries and deathes that man can deuiſe. Wherefore the nature of man being euer more and more corrupted, ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; therewithall driuen by the violent inticement of ſin, and perſwaſion of the diuell, it is not poſsible with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the mightie aſsiſtance of Gods ſpirite, but that iniquitie ſhould not onely abound, but euen nowe be growen to the full.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeake more particularlie of the ſinnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, againſt man, and againſt our owne ſelues; I ſay, that they doe now by meanes of Antichriſt and his adherentes more infinitely abounde, than euer. Whereby it may euidently appeare, that the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of all thinges is at hande. Was not <hi>Lucifer</hi> an Angell of light, and deſired in his heart to be but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with God? And is Antichriſt any more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, ſomewhat lower than the Angels, and yet exalteth
<pb facs="tcp:7396:12"/>himſelfe aboue God? Did <hi>Adam</hi> breake any more commaundements of God then one, when he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed and caſt out of Paradice? But do not we daylie breake all the commaundements of God, and yet are not once aſhamed of our nakedneſſe? Was not <hi>Cayn</hi> counted a reprobat, becauſe he was angrie with God, and killed his owne brother about the accepting of their ſacrifices? But are not wee euery day vexed and diſquieted againſt God, if but the leaſt attempt that we go about ſucceed not according to our deſire? But bee there not alſo as greeuous and horrible paricides and murders among vs, euen for the ſmalleſt and leaſt occaſions? Was it not counted a monſtrous and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Idolatrie of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they forgot God that had brought them out of the land of <hi>Egipt,</hi> and worſhipped a golden Calfe which they themſelues had made, becauſe that <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſeruant of God and their generall Captaine, was but fourtie dayes abſent from them. Agayne, is not the Idolatrie in theſe dayes of them that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, beyond al compariſon greater, when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him that redeemed them from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and do daylie worſhip ſtockes and ſtones, and a peece of vnleauened bread, when as Chriſt himſelfe their head and Captaine is continually preſent with them by his holy Saincts and Godhead, vntill the end of the world?</p>
            <p>Was not the infidelitie of the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> counted exceeding great, when as they beleeued not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7396:12"/>the promiſes of GOD, who had done ſo great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for them, both in <hi>Egipt</hi> and at the red Sea? For which cauſe they themſelues were deſtroyed, and their children were made to wander fourtie yeares in the wilderneſſe for the ſinnes of their fathers. But is not the infidelitie of the Chriſtians in our time much more horrible, when as GOD hath done for them farre greater thinges, then euer he did for the Children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> euen by ſending his owne Sonne for their ſakes into the world, to deliuer them from the ſlauerie of Sathan, and euerlaſting deſtruction of bodie and ſoule; where he keepeth them as the apple of his eye, from being conſumed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about them; when hee talketh with them daylie and familiarlie from heauen out of his holie worde, when hee feedeth them from aboue with his owne precious bodie; when hee indueth them with grace ſupernaturall by his holie ſpirite; when hee bleſſeth them with all his benefites both bodily and ghoſtly; and yet are not we more vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, vnthankfull, and vnfruitfull, than the Children of <hi>Iſraell?</hi> They beleeued not, becauſe the time of the promiſes vnto them made, was not yet perfourmed: wee beleeue not when all the propheſies deliuered to vs in the Scriptures, bee alreadie fulfilled. They grudged and wauered, when they were wandering in the deſolate wilderneſſe, wanting many pleaſures and delights of this deceiuing life: wee miſtruſt, though we now be in a delightfull and pleaſant land,
<pb facs="tcp:7396:13"/>and abound in all worldlie comforts that can be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for man. They miſdoubted the firſt comming of <hi>Meſsias,</hi> becauſe the words proceded fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouths of men: but manie of vs beleeue not his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, though he himſelfe haue abſolutely promiſed, and ſhewed the tokens of the ſame, by his owne holy word. And ſo iniquitie and incredulitie abound this day, beyond all the ages and times of the worlde. Wherefore the Lord muſt of neceſsitie come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer his people from the intollerable burden thereof.</p>
            <p>Againe, was not the diſobedience and murmuring of <hi>Iſrael</hi> againſt God, and againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſo incomparable great, as the earth opened and ſwallowed vp the principall leaders of that conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and all their habitations and families? Yea, ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie was the Lord with this ſinne, that had it not been for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſake, hee woulde then haue diſpatched the whole generation of them from the face of the earth. But if we will but looke into the Chriſtianitie, &amp; ſee what diſobedience there is to the commandementes of God, what continuall murmuringes againſt him, what daylie diſcontentments with the bleſsings that he ſendeth: what rebellions, conſpiracies, and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt the Princes which be his Lieutenaunts, yea, what treaſons &amp; trecheries againſt the royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Souereignes. Nay what banding there is againſt Chriſt &amp; his Church, to roote out both him and his holie word, that neither of them ſhould haue anie more being in the world, wee ſhall finde that the burden of iniquitie is at this day ſo exceeding heauie,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7396:13"/>as the foundations of the world being ſo farre out of courſe, muſt needs fall to ruine and deſolation.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, within what age and memorie of man is is knowen; in what writings ethnicke or chriſtian hath it bene founde; nay, by what place of Scripture can it be prooued, (eſpeciallie ſince the former deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the world by waters) that the ſinne of luſt &amp; fornication did ſo generally inuade the whole world, as it doth at this preſent daye? What ſinne doeth ſo ſpeedely procure the diſpleaſure of God, the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vngodly, and the finall ende of all thinges by fier, as doth the flame of luſt and concupiſence? But what needeth mee to recite the greatneſſe of this ſinne, when the vengeance and puniſhments that God hath brought, and daily doth bring vpon fornicatours and adulterers, both among Infidels and Chriſtians, in euerie age, and in all families and kingdomes, doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently ſhew the ſame. And albeit we knowe, that for this ſinne ſpecially, God burned vp the cities of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrhe</hi> into aſhes; that he ſlewe in one day three or foure and twentie thouſand <hi>Iſaclites,</hi> for committing that abhomination with the daughters of <hi>Moab:</hi> albeit I ſay, we know that this ſinne ſo ſore diſpleaſeth our God, impaireth our credite, waſteth our goods, weakneth our bodies, dulleth our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, tormenteth our mindes, and worketh al manner of woe both to ſoule and bodie in this life, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inheriting of euerlaſting life in the world to come: yet doe we in this age take ſuch vile and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie pleaſure therein, as we exceede all the abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:7396:14"/>of <hi>Sodom:</hi> and therein the world may ſeeme to match all the Generations that haue gone before vs. And the greateſt cauſe why God hath not yet pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon vs the ſame or greater vengeance than he did vpon our forefathers, is becauſe hee hath nowe but a ſhort time of patience, and then commeth the day of vengeance. For he hath alreadie ſounded his Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet vnto iudgement, he hath ſignified by his prophets, he hath pronounced by his Preachers, hee hath publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by his ſignes and tokens, and hee hath opened plainelie by the word of his promiſe, that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſpeedelie like a Lion vpon his enemies, and to reward with deſtruction and vengeance, all them that worke wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>But I am aſhamed to ſpeake of the loathſome and horrible ſinne of drunkenneſſe and ſurfetting: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be diuers other ſinnes, wherein for the vileneſſe of them, men may be compared with brute beaſts: yet in this ſinne, men without all compariſon excell all beaſts and liuing creatures in the world. For beaſts being voide of all reaſon, yet doe they knowe what is neceſſarie and ſufficient for them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe they rarelie or neuer take anie more ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce than is meete for their health, although they haue neuer ſo great plentie miniſtred vnto them. But man, that is indued with reaſon and ſpeech, the two principall things whereby he is diſcerned from other beaſts, and whereby he hath the dominion of them; during the time that he is occupied in the ſinne of drunkenneſſe, he is not onelie depriued of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7396:14"/>knowledge and gouernment, that God hath giuen him aboue other creatures, but while his head is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged with wine, he hath neither the power of vnderſtanding, nor the ſenſe of feeling, that other beaſts haue. O moſt horrible and cruell ſinne, O monſtrous diſeaſe of the fleſh, howe eaſelie mighteſt thou be lefte, what little neede hath man of thee, and yet what dangerous and deadlie enormities doſt thou bring vpon him, both againſt himſelfe, againſt his neighbour, againſt the Commonweale, and againſt the commaundements of our gracious God? He that is ouerloden with wine and ſtrong drinke, foultreth in his ſpeech, reeleth too &amp; fro, falleth on the ground, or tumbleth into the ditch; the world goeth round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, ſhame doth not lay holde on him, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are aſhamed for him. The preſence of perſons doth not feare him, euerie man ſcorneth him, euerie man ſhunneth him, euerie man derideth him, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth greeue him.</p>
            <p>Againe, he whoſe head is not ſo deepelie drowned in drinke, but is ouer merie therewith, &amp; hath fraigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his bodie, and pampered his bellie, as well with meate as drinke, how ſlow is he to all vertue, &amp; how prone is he to al kind of miſchiefe? <hi>Pouertie, woe, ſtrife, ſorowe, bralling and wounds without a cauſe, followe them that delight in wine and delicate fare.</hi> And,<note place="margin">Prou. 21, Prou. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Through glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie commeth ſickeneſſe, and by ſurfetting, death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that men woulde alſo weight the greatneſſe of this ſinne, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the miſchiefs that it bringeth. For beſides that it deſtroyeth the health of the bodie,
<pb facs="tcp:7396:15"/>and ſhorteneth mans life, it alſo alienateth the minde, prouoketh anger, ſtirreth vp luſts, conſumeth riches, diſcouereth ſecrets, peruerteth iudgement: it cauſeth ſloth in the bodie, dulneſſe in wit, weakneſſe in the memorie, and vnwillingneſſe to euerie good action. The abundaunce that is conſumed by this one onelie vice, woulde ſupply all the wantes in the Common weale. The forbearing of one meale within this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of all the people but once in a yere, would feed a mightie Armie a whole moneth. The ſparing of one diſh but once in a day, of them that haue manie dainties at their table, woulde ſatisfie the poore that lie in miſerie at their gate. The ſuperfluitie of fare, that is ſpent in one dayes interteinment, would giue reliefe to all that be lame and impotent. The monie that is ſpent in ſtrong and needleſſe drinke, would pay all the duties that belong to a Prince. Neuertheleſſe, ſo vile and corrupt is the nature of man, ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately doeth hee runne into his owne fleſhly deſires, that though hee knewe his poore and needie brother ſhoulde periſh for want, that his Countrie and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale ſhould be in diſtreſſe, nay that his own life ſhould lye vpon the abſtinence of one meale, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing of one match at drinking, he would not leaue his greedie appetite. Although men at this day are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſee ſuch beaſtlineſſe in others: Albeit they are greeued when they heare of the drunkenneſſe of <hi>Noah,</hi> when his two ſonnes couered him: of <hi>Lot,</hi> when he lay with his own daughters. Although they know that death was pronounced againſt <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 10.</note> if he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7396:15"/>dronke wine or ſtrong drink;<note place="margin">Gen. 25.</note> That <hi>Eſau</hi> loſt his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for the greedineſſe of a meſſe of potage; That <hi>Balthazar</hi> in his dronkenneſſe ſawe a finger vpon the wall,<note place="margin">Dan 5.</note> that wrote the finall ende both of him and his kingdome; and that the drunken banquet of <hi>Benadab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. King 20.</note> was the deſtruction 32. Kings with all their Armie. Albeit that wo is pronounced to them,<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.</note> that riſe vp ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to follow dronkenneſſe; that wine maketh a man ſcornfull and vnquiet;<note place="margin">Pro 20. Ezech. 16. Gal. 5.</note> that fulneſſe of meate was one of the great cauſes why <hi>Sodom</hi> was deſtroyed: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, that no drunkard nor glutton ſhall inherite the kingdome of heauen, yet are not men by al theſe war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings moued, yet doe they follow the wickedneſſe thereof, and that with more greedineſſe than euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. All their felicitie is in banqueting, all their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is in drinking, all their delight is in their belly, all the paſtime of their life is in gluttonie &amp; good cheere,<note place="margin">Eſay. 22.13.</note> 
               <hi>Come</hi> (ſay they) <hi>let vs eate and drinke, and bee merie: for to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> Nothing at this day but eating, nothing but drinking, nothing but powring in of cups from morning to night, and from night to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo al their life long, without reſpect of time, or place, or holie dya, or Sabboth day; without feare of lawes, without feare of life, without feare of God, and without feare of damnation, or any hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore this vice beeing greater than euer, requireth a greater vengeance, and ſpeedier comming vnto iudgement, than euer.</p>
            <p>But I tremble at this day with horrour and greefe, when I heare the name of the Lorde to bee ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb facs="tcp:7396:16"/>and continually taken in vayne, and to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honored in euery corner. For, wheras we are ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged, that we ſhould not ſweare, neither by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, nor by the earth, nor by any other othe; ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and peruerſe is the nature of man, ſo croſſe and contratie to the will and commaundement of God, ſo vntoward to that he ſhould, and ſo readie to that hee ſhould not, that whatſoeuer he is moſt forbidden, that doth he moſt inſue. If there bee any corner, wherein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he may ſtart from the impunitie of mans lawe, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he runne headlong without regarde of any diuine prohibition, and without feare of Gods ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible iudgement and condemnation. And for this cauſe, where a publike weale hath made no expreſſe lawe for the puniſhment of ſwearing, there men make no conſcience of any othe in the world; there heauen and earth is no othe with them; there the creatures of God are nothing with them; there the Lord of hoaſts is nothing with them; the name of his bleſſed Sonne is nothing with them; nay, all the precious members of our Sauiour that ſuffered for vs, are too little for them to bee a teſtimonie of all their vntruthes, of all their vilanies, of all their abhominations that they worke in the worlde. But if they promiſe or vowe any thing which they haue any minde to perfourme, or if they would iuſtifie themſelues in any thing wherein their conſcience cleereth them, that will they affirme by that little trueth and faith which they haue: But if they be ſtirred vp vnto furie; if their bloud be warmed with ſurfeting and drunkenneſſe; if they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7396:16"/>be greedie of reuenge agaynſt ſuch as haue offended them; if they promiſe to meete vpon any wicked en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe, if it be for the ſauing of a ſmall penie in their purſe, or for defence of their credite in a playne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, in euery trifling matter, in euery vayne enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, in euery idle game, and communication, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that will they confirme with the moſt vehement and mightie othes that they can deuiſe. The bleſſed and diuine ſoule of Chriſt, the precious and deere bloud of the Lambe immaculat, and all the glorious and excellent members of Chriſt: nay, be Maieſtie of Chriſt, and of the Father himſelfe, are nothing in their vile and vnpurre lippes. This I ſay is the naughtie na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, to bee euer contrarie to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God. If GOD had commaunded vs that whatſoeuer wee promiſe, or affirme, or anſwere, or iuſtifie in this life, wee ſhould call heauen and earth to record, or his creatures, or himſelfe, or ſome of his bodily members, we ſhould neuer haue heard an othe in this worlde. But becauſe hee forbad vs all theſe thinges, and that our affirmation ſhould bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but yea and nay, therefore wee moſt impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie abuſe all his creatures, and moſt ſhamefully blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of GOD, in all our wordes, in all our affirmations, iuſtifications, and actions: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall all theſe bee a teſtimonie agaynſt vs in the day of iudgement.</p>
            <p>Looke well vnto it therfore, ye that be theſe luftie and wilfull ſwearers in the world, ye that call the
<pb facs="tcp:7396:17"/>Lorde of hoſtes ſo often to witneſſe with your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths and vanities, bee yee ſure that the Lorde is not deafe, but doth heare you: hee hath regiſtred &amp; writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp all the idle words that ye haue ſpoken, in your banqueting, in your ſurfetings, in your gamings, and in al the looſe and lewd behauiour of your liues: hee hath written in the face of euerie creature, all the teſtimonies that ye called them to witneſſe with you; much more ſhall yee finde printed in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nay, yee ſhall haue it engrauen both in your owne conſcience, and in the Maieſtie of his perſon, all the wilfull and raſh othes, wherby ye haue called him to record: and vnleſſe you ſpeedely repent you in this life, and ceaſe for euer to blaſpheme the name of God as yee haue done: yee ſhall ſhortly come before the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Iudge, where it ſhall be ſo hardly layd to your charge, as ye ſhal wiſh that the mountaines might co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you, and the earth ſhadow you from the preſence of God, whom you haue ſo highly diſpleaſed. For the horrible ſinne of ſwearing is ſo continually accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in your mouths, and the name of God and of his holy members, is ſo abuſed in your actions, as he can no longer indure the wickedneſſe thereof, but wil ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten himſelfe vnto iudgement.</p>
            <p>Now, if theſe ſinnes, beſides manie others that I might recite, doe ſo abound at this day in the hearts of men, and doe breake out ſo mightily in their actions, as the things themſelues declare, that the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is at hand; what ſhall we ſay of the ſinne of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, the roote and welſpring of all other miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7396:17"/>Wherein men at this day doe ſo farre exceed the meaſure of our forefathers, as the later wee are borne, the more corruption we haue receiued: &amp; the neerer to the day of the Lord, the leſſe affection haue we to heauenly things, and the more deſire of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vanities. And albeit this ſinne of coueting, bee ſet downe as a capital crime in the holy Scriptures, yet do we make ſmall account of the ſame. Howbeit, if the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> fled before their enimies,<note place="margin">Ioſu. 7.</note> onely for the couetouſneſſe of <hi>Achan,</hi> and that <hi>Achan</hi> himſelfe was iudicially and formally executed, becauſe he had hidden to his owne vſe ſome thinges that were accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; if <hi>Nabal</hi> the <hi>Carmelite</hi> for his couetous minde,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> in denying ſome ſuſtenance vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> and his ſeruants in time of neceſsitie, was ſtriken by God that he died; finally, if <hi>Gehezi</hi> the ſeruant of <hi>Elizeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Kings 5.</note> was puniſhed with a foule leproſie, for requiring and taking but a ſmall gifte of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Sirian,</hi> whome his Maſter had frankly &amp; freely a litle before healed of the ſame diſeaſe what deſerueth the vnſatiable mind of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in our time, that without all meaſure or ende, without feare of God, without regard of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with out remorſe of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, without ſenſe of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s griefes, be it right or wrong, whether it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne God or the Church, the Prince or the Commonweale, the father or the ſonne, neighbour or ſtraunger, friend or foe, life or death: if it may turne to our owneprofit &amp; commoditie, we ſeeke by all manner of meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine therevnto, though we die for it in this life, and be ſure of damnation in the life to come, without all
<pb facs="tcp:7396:18"/>remorſe of conſcience, or anie care of reſtitution, Howbeit all this commeth to paſſe, that the word of God may not be fruſtrate, which ſaith, that in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day iniquitie ſhall abound, and the loue towardes God and man ſhall decaie: And the abundance of all ſinne doth grow from this verie roote of coueting &amp; greedineſſe of riches. But in verie deede the meanes that this ſinne hath had to come to ſuch ripeneſſe in theſe our dayes, haue been farre greater than euer in anie Age before; For euen ſince the time that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to ſhewe foorth all other ſignes and tokens, which hee had promiſed to come againſt the ende of the world; what wayes haue men attempted, what artes haue they deuiſed to fulfill their greedie appetite and deſire? Be there anie lands that they haue not ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, or anie ſeas that they haue not ſayled? Bee there anie dangers that they haue not ventured? Is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie colde or heate that they haue not indured? Is there anie world that they haue not compaſſed; anie myne that they haue not opened, anie bloud that they haue not ſpilled; nay, anie people that they haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed to attaine to their deſire? Doe they not trauell more willinglie, more often and farther, from the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt face of the earth to the nethermoſt part of the ſame, from the Sunne riſing to the Sunne ſetting, from the South to the North, and to all the endes of the world, and all for the inſatiable deſire of golde &amp; ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, redde claie and white, than they woulde doe for the ſauegard of their owne life? And yet the more they haue, the more they want; the more they want,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7396:18"/>the more they couet: In ſuch ſort, as if the earth and ſea were emptied of their treaſures, I ſuppoſe that they woulde ſeeke to Heauen for temporall riches, which they cannot beelead vnto for the ſaluation of their ſoules. Wherefore this vice of couetouſneſſe is now ſo primie full, as it craueth an ende and diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</p>
            <p>Now come wee to the laſt token and reſtimonie of the comming of Chriſt, namelie; <hi>That the Goſpell ſhalbe preached in all the world, for a witnes vnto all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and then ſhall the ende come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I wrote before, that the reuealing of Antichriſt and man of ſinne, which ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhould be the firſt token of that ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comming of Chriſt: ſo the preaching of the Goſpell ouer all the world, both by the circumſtance of the Euangelicall hiſtorie, and by the conſequence of the thinges them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, muſt of neceſsitie bee the laſt token before his comming. And this is alſo confirmed by <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Reuelation, when he ſaith;<note place="margin">Apoc 14.</note> That he ſawe an Angell flie in the midſt of heauen, hauing the euerlaſting go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell to preach to all nations, kindreds, and people, and ſaying; <hi>Giue glorie to God, for the hower of his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come.</hi> And immediatelie after this preaching of the word, an other Angell crieth, <hi>Babylon is falne, that great Citie is falne, that made all Nations drinke of the Cup of her fornication.</hi> For if there bee no other way to make Babylon to fall, to reueale Antichriſt the enimie of Chriſt, and to baniſh the Apoſtaſie of the Church procured by the ſame Antichriſt, but the
<pb facs="tcp:7396:19"/>preaching of the word and free courſe of the Goſpek the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is there alſo no other way to inlarge the kingdom of Chriſt, &amp; to gather the Saints of God into one, but onely the free courſe and publication of the Goſpell: which by litle and litle ſhall conſume as it hath gebun the ſpirite of error and apoſtaſie of the Church, till the brightnes of Chriſtes preſence haue vtterly deſtroyed the ſame, &amp; al the authors &amp; abettors thereof. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatſoeuer other tokens ſhal be at the verie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt (as no doubt but ther ſhalbe many both in the Sunne and Moone, and ſtarres, and in al the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures of God, as behoueth in ſo great an alteration &amp; conſummation of the worlde,<note place="margin">Mat. 24. Mark. 13.</note> and as Chriſt himſelfe hath moſt effectually ſet downe in his holy word) yet this publiſhing of the Goſpel in all the world ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be the very laſt token before his comming, as it is euidently ſet down by the holy Ghoſt himſelf, when he ſaith, <hi>And then ſhal the ende come:</hi> And when the Angels after preaching of the word ſaid,<note place="margin">Apoc 14.</note> 
               <hi>The houre of iudgement is come: thruſt in thy ſythe and reape, for the harueſt is ripe.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, When Antichriſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> which exalteth himſelfe aboue me, ſhalbe reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be the principal head that hath cauſed ſo great a falling away from the truth in my Church, hee ſhall trouble and perſecute you to the death: he ſhall make nation to riſe againſt nation, for vpholding of his damnable hereſie, and hee ſhall cauſe you to bee hated for my ſake: but feare not my little ones; for when yee ſhall ſee all theſe troubles to happen, bee ye ſure that my comming, and your redemption draweth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7396:19"/>nigh. For my word ſhall runne out very ſwiftly, and in a ſhort ſpace conſume that which he by his hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and tyrannie had in many yeares contriued. He that hath cauſed al Princes to drinke of the poyſoned cuppe of his fornication, him will I ſodainly deſtroy with the breath of my mouth. Yea, and leaſt ye ſhould any longer bee deceiued by his falſe ſignes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuable errors, my word ſhall be publiſhed in all the world, and then is the time of my comming, then is the harueſt of the earth ripe, and then will I thruſt in my ſickle and reape. And this publication of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ouer all the world is the ſecond ſound vnto iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For as our Sauiour Chriſt gaue the firſt ſound, when he ſent foorth his Apoſtles, and commaunded them to teach all nations,<note place="margin">Math. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to baptize them in the name of the Father, of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt, and to plant Churches in al thoſe places which receiued the word of truth: &amp; that the fame of Chriſt and ſound of the Goſpell went foorth at that time to all lands, where any people did inhabite. So now, all things being fulfilled, that the Scriptures had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhould come to paſſe betweene the firſt warning and the ſecond; The Goſpell of our Sauiour is begun agayne to be renewed &amp; publiſhed ouer al the world, and that more freely and without perill then euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by reaſon of the godly minds and good indeuors of Chriſtian Magiſtrates. And this I ſay is the ſecond ſound of the Trompet: beſides which, wee are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no more till Chriſt himſelf enuyrond with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Angels, and in the Trompet of God &amp; voyce
<pb facs="tcp:7396:20"/>of an Archangell ſhal deſcend from heauen, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund the dead to ariſe, and ſhall gather his elect from the foure windes, and from euery part of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and from the deepe places. And as this publiſhing of the Goſpell is a moſt aſſured token of his comming, ſo by reaſon of the effects thereof, it is more notable then all the reſt. For it ſeemeth to bee but ſimple in ſhewe, but it is wonderfull in operation. It is contayned in playne and familiar termes, but it ſearcheth the very roote of the heart. It appeareth but fooliſhneſſe to the vngodlie, and to them that periſh, but it confoundeth the wiſedome and craftines of this world. It is but ſmall and of no reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men, but it driueth proud and mightie tyrants from their feates, and exalteth into their places them which ſubmit themſelues vnto it. It is but weake in ſight of the world, but it is the power of God vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in them that beleeue, and it cutteth more ſharp than a two edged ſword, ouerthrowing all the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10. verſ. 4.5 6.</note> and euery high thing that is exalted agaynſt the knowledge of God, bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the obedience of Chriſt, and hauing readie vengeance againſt all diſobedience. And it is no new Goſpell that is now preached, but it is the old Goſpell newly publiſhed. It is the ſame that the Apoſtles taught &amp; planted, but the ingratitude of the world left and contemned. If any nation at this day haue been kept in blindnes; if any haue been held fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the benefite of the Goſpell, their owne ſinnes and abhominations haue been the cauſe thereof, for that they haue wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully withheld the truth in their own vnrighteouſnes,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7396:20"/>and haue deſpiſed both God the Father &amp; his Sonne, &amp; haue wrought deſpite vnto the ſpirit of grace. For the creation both of themſelues, and of all the viſible things of the world, might make both God and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie manifeſt enough vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet would they not acknowledge him, but haue followed their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, &amp; haue turned the glory that is due vnto the only wiſe &amp; vncorruptible God, either vnto creatures farre inferior to themſelues, or els they haue worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped deuils &amp; damnable ſpirits, forſaking the true God that made both them &amp; al the world. Beſides this they cannot pleade ignorance: For vndoubtedly, the ſound of his Goſpell hath firſt or laſt gon into all lands. And though perhaps later into one countrie than into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hath God done in his wonderfull wiſedome and prouidence, who beholdeth all the nations in the world at one view, ſeeth into all their actions, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all their hearts, perceiueth who be inclined vnto any goodnes, &amp; who haue giuen ouer themſelues to a wilfull and reprobate mind. And as he beholdeth all men, ſo he calleth all men, ſome at the firſt houre, and ſome at the laſt; that he may haue mercie on whom it pleaſeth him, and may ſhut vp vnder infidelitie thoſe that are hard harted. Neuertheleſſe, if there be any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that heard not of Chriſt in the firſt ſound of the Trompet by the Apoſtles, nor in all this time that the preaching of the Goſpell hath been diſcontinued, yet now there is not doubt but in this ſecond warning &amp; publication of the word of God, through the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſes of our bleſſed Soueraign, &amp; by the care that ſhe &amp; other godly Princes of the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb facs="tcp:7396:21"/>haue to aduaunce the kingdome of Chriſt, there ſhall bee no corner within the whole circumference of the earth, but in ſhort ſpace ſhall not only haue the ſound of the Goſpell, but a perfect publication and ſpreading of the ſame, with a full knowledge of Chriſt. For the Goſpell ſhall be publiſhed ouer all the world, and then commeth the end. And vndoubtedly, if the Goſpell had been preached and taught vnto the people of <hi>America,</hi> and the lower <hi>India,</hi> by the <hi>Spanyards</hi> and <hi>Portingalls,</hi> when they firſt found out thoſe nations, with ſuch plainnes and ſimplicitie, as is done by vs in the reformed Churches, without adding of Images, or ſuperſtitions, or vanities, no leſſe peeuiſh and vngodly, then the abhominations that thoſe Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels themſelues had before vſed, the kingdome of Chriſt had long before this day been receiued and ſpread ouer all thoſe large and ample Territories. Wherefore the more greeuous ſhall bee their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that haue ſo mocked and deceiued them: and the greater is the mercie of God if he impute not their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance vnto them.</p>
            <p>Now that wee haue breefly declared all the ſignes and tokens, which the holy Ghoſt hath promiſed in the Scriptures to come to paſſe before the ende of the world, wee muſt alſo with the like perſpicuitie, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether this be not the time, or very neere ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto that Chriſt ſhall come agayne in glorie to iudge both the quick and the dead, which is the ſecond part of this diſcourſe. For albeit that he hath ſet downe all theſe tokens of his comming ſo exactly and in ſuch
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7396:21"/>order, as it is vnpoſsible, but that anie man capable of reaſon may vnderſtande when the laſt token is fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: yet hath he alſo confirmed the ſame by other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible reaſons, drawen partlie from ſuch thinges as we ſenſiblie and daylie perceiue, and partlie from his owne power and omnipotencie. <hi>Learne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the figge tree when the branches bee tender, and hath put forth leaues, for then ye be ſure that the ſummer is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hand.</hi> Againe, <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall periſh, but my word ſhall not periſh.</hi> As if he might ſay: When all theſe tokens that I haue ſpoken of be fulfilled, ye ſhall be ſure that I will then come: and the laſt token before my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is, That the Goſpel of my kingdom ſhalbe prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in all the world, for a witneſſe vnto all Nations: And there ſhall not be a kingdome in the worlde, but either at the firſt ſounding of my word, or at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſhall heare that I am the Sauiour and redeemer of mankinde. Beholde I haue ſpoken it: Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe away, before one iot of my worde paſſe. Theſe I ſay be the verie tokens &amp; times before his comming. Albeit to ſpeake of the hower, or day, or month, nay of the yere it ſelfe wherm he wil com, were high pride and preſumption: ſeeing there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor angel that knoweth it. But this we know for certeintie: that manie Ages paſt, the Goſpell was publiſhed welneere in all <hi>Aſia, Aphrica</hi> and <hi>Europe:</hi> a number of which Nations for their vnthankfulneſſe were depriued of the benefit thereof, and manie other are falne into great Apoſtaſie. Alſo we ſee it plaine, that in this age of ours, the glad tidings of Chriſt, hath
<pb facs="tcp:7396:22"/>after ſome ſort bin caried vnto al the barbarous natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the nether part of the world: &amp; we liue in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual hope that in ſhort ſpace it ſhalbe more ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerly &amp; more vniuerſallie publiſhed tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hetherto it hath bin; which being proclaimed, we may then bee bolde to ſay, that Chriſt is at the verie point of his comming. And yet neuertheles al that is no hindra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but that it behoueth vs both thus day, &amp; to morrow, &amp; euerie day &amp; night &amp; hower, to watch &amp; be readie with our lampes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, left the Bridegrome take vs vpon the ſodaine &amp; vnprouided of oyle; &amp; ſo while we expect yet ſome longer time of his comming, we bee quite excluded out of the kingdome of heauen. Al theſe things haue I affirmed and prooued out of the infallible worde of God, &amp; by that which we haue ſeen with our eyes, &amp; do vnderſtand of our owne knowledge to be alreadie come to paſſe, moſt agreeablie to the worde of God. Wherby we may be aſſured, that if anie thing be yet to come that the Scriptures haue promiſed touching the end of the world, the ſame ſhal ſhortly &amp; in his due time be performed. And this was my ſpecial purpoſe in this Treatiſe to proue: that becauſe the fooliſh, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie, &amp; vnbeleeuing nature of men, is in theſe daies beyond all other ages and times before, ſo curious to ſearch &amp; inquire for the time of Chriſtes comming, which time God hath reſerued to himſelfe; I might draw them, (as much as is poſsible) from ſeeking the ſame at the hands of men, (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without the help of Gods ſpirite, there proceedeth nothing that is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, or true, or godlie) &amp; ſend them to the moſt true,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7396:22"/>and certain, and vndoubted propheſie of the word of God. Neuertheles I am not ignorant, that there be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo manie humane reaſons, manie probable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectures, manie te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral ſignes &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; many ſufficient argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the end of the world, that do concurre with the propheſie of the ſcriptures: al which as long as they ſerue to iuſtify &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme whatſoeuer Chriſt, the Prophetes &amp; Apoſtles haue promiſed concerning the ſame, we muſt rather giue credite vnto them, than reiect &amp; condemne them. Among which are al thoſe reaſons which are commonly made to ratifie the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Elias,</hi> that the world ſhall not continue the full of 6000. yeres: which propheſie though it be not in the ſcriptures, but cited by the Rabbins, yet becauſe all the other parts of the ſame Propheſie haue ſucceeded euery thing in his due time &amp; that it doth ſo well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the tokens, that Chriſt ſhewed for the end of the world, and with that ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Thoſe dayes ſhalbe ſhortened for the elect ſake:</hi> we muſt imbrace the ſame as a true prognoſticate, religiouſly deſcended from that holie Author.</p>
            <p>But in verie deede in this propheſie of <hi>Elias</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a large field to prooue the neereneſſe of the day of iudgement: howbeit I wil not walke much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, becauſe I knowe it hath been exactlie handled of manie. Onelie this I ſay; that the Scripture it ſelfe confirmeth, and infallible reaſon prooueth, and ſo manie tokens both of heauen aboue, and of the earth beneath teſtifie that the world ſhall not laſt to the end of ſixe thouſand yeeres.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:23"/>
            <p>And ſo much the rather, when we plainelie ſee all the tokens of the latter day to be now welneere fulfilled. And I haue proued, that there are not aboue 70. yeres paſt or thereabout ſince the laſt and moſt reuealing of Antichriſt: That is to ſay, ſince he was openlie, freelie and without feare publiſhed to be that ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Within which time, the tokens that Chriſt ſpoke of concerning the ende of the worlde, are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhewed, and lacke but little of a perfect fulfilling. And doe we thinke, that when ſo great and ſo manie things haue been accompliſhed in ſo ſhort a ſpace as 70. yeres, that the verie litle or nothing which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſhould be in performing 400. yeeres and moe, which are to finiſh vp the number of 6000. yeres? Or may we not not referre that ſaying of Chriſt <hi>(This gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhall not be paſt, till all theſe things be fulfilled.</hi> And againe: <hi>For the choſens ſake theſe dayes ſhalbe ſhortened)</hi> as well to this third age of the world, as to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which was but 50. yeres after? As if he ſhould ſay: In this latter age of the world, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallie towards the ende thereof, when Antichriſt is reuealed, and Sathan which is the diuell is looſed, there ſhalbe ſo great famines, plagues, &amp; earthquakes, ſo great and hortible perſecutions, ſuch leagues and conſpiracies of Princes againſt my Church, ſo manie falſe Prophetes to deceaue the worlde, ſuch hating and betraying one of another, yea and ſuch trouble and vexation on euerie ſide, beſides the iniquitie that ſhall then ſo mightelie abound; that if it be poſsible the verie choſen may be deceaued.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7396:23"/>
            <p>Wherfore, for their ſakes I wil ſhorten thoſe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome dayes, and will cut off a part of this latter age, ſo that it ſhal not be equall to the other ages that went before.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what wonderfull alterations haue wee heard of and ſeene in the world, ſince the memorie of man? What chaunge in the nature of the creatures? what mutation both in the actions and affections of men, and in the accidents of this life and occurrents of eſtates; ſuch as our forefathers in many hundreth yeares before neuer heard of? All which things, ſince they moſt and chiefly happened or began about the time that the Goſpell in our age was reuiued by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and when the kingdome of Chriſt began to be reſtored, they bee manifeſt tokens of the ende of the world.</p>
            <p>Hath not theſe many and mightie Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scotland, Denmarke, Swethland, Poland, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Belgica,</hi> and a great part of the large kingdome of <hi>Fraunce</hi> (all which be as much as the reſt of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) retired themſelues, and been reclaymed within this ſpace from the Romiſh bondage, and from Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianitie to the true worſhipping of Chriſt, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing of the Goſpell preached vnto them?</p>
            <p>Was not the Arte and skill of Printing deuiſed by Chriſtians, and ſpecially practiſed in our time; by the meanes wherof, though not only, yet chiefly all other Religions in the world are found to bee moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Idolatrous: and only the true and ſincere wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Chriſt magnified and extolled in all the
<pb facs="tcp:7396:24"/>world? Were not all the learned tongues and langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges renued by Chriſtians in our time, from a rude bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſme (wherein they had many ages been a ſleepe) to an excellent and perfect fourme both of ſpeaking and writing?</p>
            <p>Is not the deſire of Chriſtians in our time, more earneſtly bent to ſeeke a perfection of all Arts and Sciences, and a more exquiſite forme of Religion then euer was in any age before vs ſince the ſincere times of the Primitiue Church?</p>
            <p>Were not all the order and maner of Inſtruments and habiliments of warre and warfare in our age, wel neere contrarie to that it was before; eſpecially by the deuiſe of gunnes, which the deuill together with his deliuerance out of bondage, deuiſed for the ſpeedie deſtruction of mankind, and great effuſion of bloud; all making way to the ſecond comming of Chriſt our King?</p>
            <p>Was not the finding out of the newe, or (as I may ſay) of the nether world, by the indeuour and trauell of Chriſtians in our time, one of the moſt wonderfull accidents that hath happened ſince the time of Chriſt: and euen as a ſigne and token before the latter day; that GOD which hath ſhut vp thoſe nations ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ages before in vnbeleefe, would now yet in the latter time call them to the knowledge of his Sonne: if any perhappes would hearken to his word, that they alſo might bee ſaued, and healed by the death of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Is it not likewiſe a ſpeciall token of the end of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7396:24"/>world, that ſuch extraordinarie Starres and Comets, ſuch ſtraunge and rare Coniunctions of the Planets, ſuch meruellous remouings of earth, whereof no mortall man can giue any naturall reaſon; together with mightie ouerflowinges of the Sea, whereby whole Countries and people are deſtroyed?</p>
            <p>But is it not as great a ſigne and token hereof, that within ſo fewe as fifteene yeares now to come, there ſhall happen fiue Eclipſes of the Sunne, beſides many others of the Moone; ſuch and ſo terrible as the like neuer happened within ſo ſhort a ſpace ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world?</p>
            <p>Doth not alſo the ſodaine decay of mans ſtrength, and ſtature, &amp; age, together with the vnwilling mind he hath to all godlines, vertue, and charitable actions, prognoſticate vnto vs any leſſe than the things before?</p>
            <p>Moreouer, do not the trees, the plants, the hearbes and fruits, and all other ſenceleſſe things of the earth, which ſhould bee for the comfort of man, moſt ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie ſhewe vnto vs by the decay of their ſtrength, of their taſte and vertue (which not long ſince they had in greater meaſure) that within a ſhort time, there ſhall be no more vſe of them? Nay, doth not the earth it ſelf complayne, that ſhe hath powred out of her bowells in a manner all the ſtore of her treaſures and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, wherewith ſhe was fraighted for the vſe of man? Yea, do not all the creatures of God earneſtly expect when the Sonne of God ſhall appeare, that they alſo may be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bondage of corruption?</p>
            <p>But ſhall wee not account this alſo to bee a great
<pb facs="tcp:7396:25"/>ſigne of the ende of the world, that it pleaſed God in this age and neuer before, both to indue man with knowledge, and to leade him, as it were by the hand, about the whole compaſſe of the earth: That when he had ſeene all, and compaſt all, and yet found all to be nothing but trouble, and vanitie, and vexation of minde, by ſea and land, &amp; in all places where he came, he might glorifie his Creator and Sauiour, which had giuen ſo excellent guiftes, and vertues, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ciuilitie, and ſo iuſt a Religion vnto his Chriſtian people, before ſo many and ſo great na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which in compariſon of them, liued without God, without faith, and without all humanitie; and might the rather bee drawne from the loue of this earthly manſion, to long for the day of Chriſt, and to bee tranſlated to a more ioyfull and euerlaſting habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</p>
            <p>To be ſhort: The number of Prophets that GOD doth daylie ſend to admoniſh all people of the latter day, and to giue them warning to be in a readines; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they teach no lyes, but ſuch things as they finde in the word of God, are no leſſe to bee beleeued then thoſe that propheſied of the firſt comming of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To make an ende hereof, the opinions, or rather firme beleefe of ſondrie ſeuerall learned &amp; wiſe men, ſo farre diſtant aſunder by places, but ſo neerely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring together by the vnitie of their iudgements, and conſent of their ſpirits as touching the comming of Chriſt, do declare, that the Bridegrome is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now comming, and craue vs to wayt for him all houres
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7396:25"/>of the day and night, that we may enter with him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mariage feaſt.</p>
            <p>Where bee now theſe Atheiſts? where bee theſe mockers? where be thoſe that walke after their own luſts, and ſay; <hi>where is the promiſe of his comming?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the winter blaſts are now gone, and the comfort of the ſpring is come: The Lord ſhall come ſpeedelie foorth like a Lion out of his denne, and will be auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of them that ſpeake blaſphemie, and will deſtroy all the workers or wickedneſſe: Beholde the Arke is now welneere finiſhed, the number is accompliſhed, the Church eſtabliſhed, the choſen confirmed: The trumpet hath ſounded: The kings ſonne muſt be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: The feaſt is prepared, the bidden gueſts haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed: All ſorts of people in all the high waies of the world are gathered, the wedding is furniſhed: The king and the bridegroome are comming: The earth and the ſea ſhall yeeld vp their dead: the ſonne of man ſhall appeare in the cloudes: he ſhal come with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glorie: Angels without number ſhall attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: All nations of the worlde ſhall drawe vnto him: The godlie ſhall triumph and reioyce in him: The generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the wicked ſhal tremble to ſee him: The godlie ſhal ſtand at his right hand, the wicked on his left: Heauen ſhalbe opened, the earth ſhalbee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, the ſea ſhalbe dried: The Sunne &amp; the Moone ſhalbe darkened, and all the powers of heauen ſhalbee moued: The ſonne of God ſhall ſit on his throne, the wicked ſhall receaue the iudgement of death, and the faithfull bee carried into the euerlaſting Kingdome.
<pb facs="tcp:7396:26"/>Wherefore the Lord ſhall come &amp; not tarie. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſignes of his comming, &amp; thoſe ſignes he hath ſent: He promiſed that he would come immediatelie after thoſe ſignes; wherefore thoſe ſignes beeing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, hee will come, and that ſodainlie like a mightie tempeſt. For heauen and earth ſhall faile, but one iot of his promiſe ſhall not faile. Wherefore, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as wee ſee ſo manie of the promiſes alreadie fulfilled, let vs be patient in the reſt, and not murmure againſt him as the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, leaſt a ſodaine deſtruction come vpon vs, as it did vpon them, and we be caſt aliue both bodie and ſoule into the bottomleſſe pit.</p>
            <p>They which beleeue not in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Chriſt, doe imitate the fooliſh exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Iulius Ceſar,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often warned before to take heed to himſelf, leaſt ſome great treaſon were wrought againſt him in the Ides of March, made but a mock thereof the ſame day that hee was ſlaine: ſaying to ſome of his familiars, which counſelled him not to go that day into the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate houſe; Why (ſaith he) they haue tolde mee this good while, that I ſhould be in danger when the Ides of March were come: they are come, and yet I am ſafe; I ſaith one, they are come, but they are not yet paſt: And ſo by his owne follie &amp; negligence he was the ſame day ſlaine. In like manner, theſe that doe but mocke at the Lords comming, do ſee (indeed) that al the ſigns which were promiſed ſhould come to paſſe, are founde to bee true: but yet becauſe Chriſt is not come, together with the ſignes, they thinke perhaps
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7396:26"/>that he will not come. But ô ye fooles; ye ſee them to be come indeed: but ye ſee them not yet finiſhed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ye ſee them ſo ſoone ended, as ye ſhal ſee the promiſe of his comming iuſtified.</p>
            <p>Some motions yee had perhaps this laſt yeere, to think vpon that day, more than ye be accuſtomed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great expectation of the Propheſie of the yere 1588; and for that ye heard by manie probable reaſons and coniectures of men (drawen from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and agreement of times, from the coniunctions of planets, which threaten either finall deſtruction or wonderfull alteration, and from the equalitie of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the yeeres of the worlde 5550 and 5555, which iumpe with the yeres of Chriſt 1588 and 1593) that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the world ſhould then ende, or elſe verie ſtrange things ſhould then happen. Howbeit this yere being paſt, yee ſeeme now to liue more ſecurelie, yee feare God leſſe, yee care leſſe for religion, yee delight more in vanities, yee ſinne more greedelie, yee prouoke Gods wrath more greeuouſlie, yee runne more head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into damnation: and yee ſing your olde tune; <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming</hi> more reprochfullie, than euer yee did before.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles, if ſo manie and ſo ſtrange things hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that yere, as the like did not in ſo ſhort ſpace in many ages before? &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing no more knowledge therof, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which could be gathred by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture of the ſtars, &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paring time with times, what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects do we think ſhal folow vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſure &amp; infallible propheſie, warranted by the ſpirit of God himſelfe in
<pb facs="tcp:7396:27"/>the canonicall ſcriptures? If the ſtarres that are but cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures, can point to the time when God will worke ſuch mighty operations in other of his creatures, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that yere they did: whereby the proud &amp; luſtie mindes of mightie Monarchs are abated, wherby pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant and ſtrong armies are diſſolued, whereby the moſt inuincible nauies and ſtrong caſtles of the ſea be deſtroyed, whereby the leagues &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracies of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhalbe made fruſtrate, wherby they that haue plaid ſo manie horrible tragedies in the Church, and haue cauſed the bloud of ſo manie hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſands to be ſpilled, ſhal the ſame yeere finiſh their daies, ſome by bloud, ſome by death: Nay if the pore herrings of the ſea, haue this yere brought vs letters of warning from God, written vpon the ſkins of their little bodies, that Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; that quickly, what think we ſhal the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gods eternal promiſe, or the leaſt word that proceedeth out of his mouth bring to paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al the tyrants and blood ſuckers of this worlde, againſt all the enemies of his Church and religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all them that make but a mocke at the glorious comming of Chriſt, againſt all the ſtrong and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Cities of the earth: yea, and againſt the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the whole globe of the world? But ye my maſters that giue ſo great credit to the reuolutions of the heauens, and to the threatning of the ſtarres &amp; pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, look wel to your ſelues from henceforth, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that the Lord hath promiſed very ſhortly to com himſelfe and call you to a reckoning, hee hath put al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo into his creatures new accidents, the effects where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7396:27"/>ſhall continue not one but one and twentie yeeres at the leaſt (if the Lorde come not before) and thoſe greater than haue euer bin ſince the world was made, the ſtraungenes whereof ſhall amaſe you, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof ſhall trouble you, when ye ſhall ſee the Sunne and Moone ſo often and in ſo ſhort time eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; when you ſhall ſee the brightnes of heauen at noone time darkened; when God ſhall powre out his wrath aboundantly by plagues and famines, by winds and tempeſtes, by fearefull ouerflowings of waters, and by the ruine and deſtruction of ſome Prouinces; when ye ſhall perceiue the ſtrength of all creatures di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, when the earth will not bring foorth her benefites, when by this time all truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes will be vaniſhed, all loue and ſocietie among men will bee diſſolued, when all men will altogether loue themſelues, and no man will any whit loue another, when naturall affection of men towards their owne will bee proſtrate, when all obedience to God and to Magiſtrates, to parents and maiſters, to Kingdomes and Common weales will be aboliſhed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing will bee done for duetie and conſcience, but all for feare and neceſsitie, when all truth, all charitie, and all goodnes will be abandoned; and when there ſhall be nothing but pride, enuie, diſsimulation, oppreſsion, luſt and couetouſnes in all the whole earth; when the earth it ſelfe will craue at the hands of GOD, Come Lord Ieſus, come quicklie, and deliuer me from this intolerable burden, which the foundation that I am builded vpon, namely, thy heauenly word, is not able
<pb facs="tcp:7396:28"/>anie longer to beare. Wherefore, If Chriſt haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered vnto vs, vpon whom the latter endes of the world are come, all the ſignes and tokens which he promiſed of his comming, If he haue ſent Preachers into the world to proclaime the Goſpell of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; If he haue reuiued as it were his owne name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that laie hidden in Images and dumme Idolls; If he haue reſumed vnto himſelfe his owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that was attributed vnto men and Saincts depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this life; If he haue reuealed that man of ſinne that taketh the whole office of Chriſt vpon him; If he haue ſent all the plagues, and famines, and earthquakes, that his wiſedome and counſell deuiſed beſt for the fatherly correction of his people before the iudgement: If nations and kingdomes which are either enemies to his Goſpell, or ſtraungers from his Church, haue banded themſelues againſt the Lord and againſt the generation of the godlie: If the father haue been againſt the ſonne, and the mother againſt the daughter, and brother againſt brother, for the name of Chriſt: If many falſe Prophets haue come in the name of Chriſt, &amp; taught the people ſhameful for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries when the Lord neuer ſent them: If men betray one another, and hate and perſecute one another for their conſcience ſake: If iniquitie be ſo filled vp with the meaſure of it ſelfe, as it can hardly bee any more augmented: Finally, if the preaching of the Goſpell, be at this day carried from one kingdome to another welneere vnto the ende of the world; and all theſe things to be the tokens of Chriſtes comming: And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7396:28"/>if ſo manie ſtraunge thinges haue happened beſides in theſe our daies, that haue not done the like in manie ages before, and all theſe in the Church, and concerning the Church, and moſt agreeable to the time of Chriſtes owne propheſie. Then is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond warning of the Trompet ſounded vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>It is high time therefore to awake out of ſleepe, and to ſlumber no more in the cogitations of vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe: It is time that wee ſhould caſt off the cares of this life, and make our ſelues readie for the daie of the Lord: It is time, yea more then time that wee ſhould caſt away the workes of darkneſſe, and put on the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of light: It is time that wee ſhould laie awaie all filthineſſe and ſinne; for now is our ſaluation nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then when wee firſt beleeued. The axe is now put to the roote of the tree: that euen now, wee muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bring foorth fruite, or els bee cut downe and caſt into the fire. Behold, now is the acceptable time, now is the daie of ſaluation, now will the Lorde ſhewe himſelfe a mightie GOD, and his name ſhall be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified in all the world. He came at the firſt, and wee knewe him not: beholde, he commeth againe, and all men ſhall knowe him: he came before ſimplie to take our nature vpon him, and to dye for our ſinnes; but he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth againe, as a conquerour to be reuenged of his enemies, and as a bountifull Prince to reward his Subiects: He came into the world, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had made, but the world would not receiue him, becauſe it was not worthv of him. Wherfore hauing
<pb facs="tcp:7396:29"/>wrought the work of our redemption, he aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vp vnto his Father, where by his holie ſpirit he hath go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned, kept, and preſerued his Church one thouſand and well neere ſixe hundred yeares, and now he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in his own perſon to call all men to an accompt, and to cite all men to his Iudgement; and thoſe that haue vſed their talents well in this life, ſhall be ſure of an eternall reward in his kingdome:<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> but if they haue been negligent and vnprofitable ſeruants, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out care of the Lords comming, he will caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vttermoſt darknes, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. There ſhall be no Lord, no King, no Emperour, nor Pope vpon the earth, that ſhall bee exempt from this Iudgement. Can any Prince or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the world compare himſelfe in brightnes and glorie vnto <hi>Lucifer</hi> that glorious Angell, yet he might not eſcape the iudgement of GOD, but the higher he was in glorie, the greater was the ſhame of his fall.</p>
            <p>Remember therefore O ye Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates, and ye that haue charge and rule of Gods people; whom God hath made his Liutenants gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall within your owne dominions, remember that the Lord is comming, and will call you to an accompt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of his Iudgement: The greater your Kingdomes and Territories be, the greater is the rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning that he requireth of you: and the more abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute you bee in commaunding all, the more are you bound to giue an accompt for. Ye are the Caeſars, to whom <hi>Paule</hi> appealed, from you lieth no appeale to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7396:29"/>anie ſuperior in this life. As the Lord hath deliuered vnto your cuſtodie the greateſt number of Talents, ſo he looketh to reape at your hands the greateſt gaines.</p>
            <p>It pitieth me to temember the woful and greeuous ſtate of all mortall men in this miſerable life, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate and dangerous caſe wherein they liue, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and imminent perills that they fall into, the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold temptations, vexations, and diſquietnes of mind that they are brought into, the continuall inticements of the fleſh and the diuell that they enter into, beſides the raſh, and furious, and vngodlie actions, that they deſperatelie runne into; That when they ſhall ſhortlie ſtand before the Tribunall ſeate, and their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience iuſtlie accuſing them thereof, there ſhalbe no wiſedome, no policie, no counſell, no eloquence of the tongue, that can excuſe or ſatisfie the leaſt offence of this life: This is the generall ſtate of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</p>
            <p>But alas for griefe, that Princes ſhould both nowe, and then alſo before the Iudgement ſeate, be in more wofull caſe, than all other perſons and ſubiects of this mortall life; That they ſhould bee in greater daunger than all men liuing; that they ſhoulde bee ſubiect to more miſcarying and miſhaps; than all men liuing; that they ſhoulde haue more vexations, diſquietneſſe, and cares of minde, than all men liuing; that tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the fleſh, that prouocations vnto luſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of pleaſures, ſhoulde take more holde of them, than of all men liuing; and that the way vnto all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie
<pb facs="tcp:7396:30"/>actions ſhould be more open vnto them, than to all men liuing: And of all theſe thinges muſt they ſhortlie yeelde an account, together with all men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. And yet beholde when the Awdit is ended for this, &amp; a <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> for all matters concerning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, there is a new inditement framed againſt them, wherein they muſt bee called to an other reckoning. Then ſhall the Regiſter of all their gouernement bee read before them: then will it be ſeene whether they haue miniſtred Iuſtice vnto their people: That is to ſay; Whether they haue hearde the fatherleſſe and oppreſſed, when they haue cried vnto them; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue taken notice of ſuch appeales, as haue ben made vnto them; Whether they haue puniſhed vngodlie and corrupt Iudges, which ſolde their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes for ſiluer, and the righteous for a poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde; Whether they haue ſpared the innocent bloud, and not pardoned them that runne on ſtill in wickedneſſe; Whether in all their publique enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, they haue reſpected the glorie of GOD, more than their owne commodities; Whether they haue nurſed, protected, and defended the Churche of GOD to the vttermoſt of their power; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue preſerued it from all hereſies, errours, ſchiſmes, and corruptions; Whether they haue pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed thoſe Rulers of the Churche, that cauſe the trueth of GOD to bee euill ſpoken of, for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe: Finallie, whether in all their actions, both at home and abroade, priuate and publique in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7396:30"/>the Churche and Common-weale, they haue done all thinges with a faithfull and ſinceere heart, and with the teſtimonie of a pure and good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Which if they haue, they ſhalbe coheires with Chriſt, and ſhall reigne with him in glorie and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for euermore: otherwiſe they ſhall ſtande among the guiltie ſinners, &amp; receaue iudgement of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation according to their merites.</p>
            <p>Next vnto Kinges and abſolute Princes, muſt come to a reckoning before the chiefe Iudge Chriſt Ieſus, the Gouernours of the Churche, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Prouinces and particular places, to whome the Prince for his owne diſcharge hath committed his authoritie, to ſee that GOD bee truelie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and Iuſtice among his ſubiectes duelie exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</p>
            <p>And therefore yee my reuerent Fathers of the Churche, yee, whoſe office it is both to teach, and feede, and gouerne the Churche vnder your charge: Chriſt will ſhortlie call you to a ſtraight accompt; Firſt, whether yee came into your office by a plaine and direct waye, or els ſtole into it by ſome cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſiniſter meanes; Whether yee deſired the office of a Biſhop for the goodneſſe of the worke, or for the gayne and profite of the liuing; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee ſet before your eyes, the benefite of the Church, and aduancement of the Goſpell, more than the honour and dignitie that is attributed vnto your calling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7396:31"/>
            <p>The ſeconde Article wherein yee muſt trie your ſelues before the Supreame Biſhoppe, is, Whether you haue indeuoured as farre as in you lyeth, to cleanſe the whole Church vnder you, of all vngodlie worſhip &amp; worſhippers in the ſame: And whether ye haue been carefull to appeaſe al ſchiſmes and contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies to the vttermoſt of your power; whether yee haue ſincerelie and diligentlie preached Chriſt, as hee hath preſcribed in his holie word; whether yee haue weeded out of your whole gouernments, all infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, vngodlie, ſchiſmaticall, yea (and as much as in you lieth) all vnlearned Paſtors, which either by their wicked examples offend, corrupt and marre their flocke, or els be altogether careleſſe and negligent of them; whether ye haue executed all the cenſures of the Church, with a faithfull and ſingle heart &amp; hand, without all fauour and corruption, for the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the glorie of God, and edifieng of die whole congregation.</p>
            <p>Item, whether you haue remooued or reformed all ſuch your Commiſſaries and other meane officers, (if anie ſuch you haue) that by their corrupt and aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritious proceedings, haue cauſed the moſt iuſt, moſt holie, and moſt pure religion of Chriſt, to bee blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed and hated among the enemies of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: and haue giuen ſo great an offence to the reſt of the Church, as manie haue runne into greeuous ſchiſmes and verie damnable opinions, by reaſon of the ſame.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:7396:31"/>
            <p>Likewiſe in all iuſt appeales made vnto you, whether you haue in charitie and conſcience indeuoured with all care and diligence to reforme all things that haue been wronged by your inferiour officers. Finally, whether ye haue fed the hungrie, clothed the naked, and lodged the harborleſſe; and whether to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of your liuing, ye haue been as liberall to the poore and impotent members of Chriſt, as carefull to aduaunce your ſelues and yours with worldly ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and honors. And thus, whether yee haue in all thinges indeuoured to the vttermoſt of your power, both by your ſound doctrine, by example of your owne life, and by your faithfull and vpright gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to walke worthie of your vocation, and haue kept the vnitie of the Spirit in the bond of peace. In al theſe things ſhall ye ſhortlie be examined and tried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the triumphant Iudge Chriſt Ieſus. Againe, ye that bee the gouernours of Prouinces, and all other Iudges and great officers, vpon whom dependeth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the liues, or the goods, or the cauſes of other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; albeit the moſt of you haue long time eſcaped the temporall ſword, yet ſhall you not now eſcape the laſt iudgement of God. For the bloud of the fatherles and widdowes haue cryed vp to the Lord of hoaſts, and he commeth to take an account of your vngodlie and vncharitable iudgements. Shall not your owne conſciences in that day accuſe you, aſ much as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand witneſſes; that you fled from iudgement and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted equitie; That ye build vp Syon with bloud,<note place="margin">Malach 3.</note> and Ieruſalem with wickedneſſe; That ye heads haue
<pb facs="tcp:7396:32"/>iudged for reward, and that ye Prieſtes haue taught for hier, and ye Prophets haue propheſied for monie: That ye haue contemned the low eſtate of the poore, &amp; feared to execute Iuſtice againſt the mightie: That ye haue often preuented the trueth of the cauſe, by a contrarie impreſsion and conceipt in your minde: That ye haue been more carried with the faire intiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of mans eloquence, than with a plaine and ſimple declaration of the trueth, That ye haue either ſtayed your iudgement by letters, or wearied your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by charges, or conſumed them by delayes, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them by your ſpeeches, or mocked them by your vanities, or driuen them to diſpaire by your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice. Finally, that ye haue not onlie ſeene the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and extortion and ſcraping of pettie clarkes and inferiour miniſters, which ye might haue redreſſed, but that ye your ſelues alſo haue bin partakers of their ſinnes. Shall not all theſe things bee layd open before your eyes in that great and terrible daie?</p>
            <p>Generally, all ye that be rich &amp; abound with goods and poſſeſsions in this life, leaue off the greedie deſire of monie, and diſpoſe well of the riches that ye haue: Make ye friends while ye maie, of your vnrighteous Mammon, that ye be not taken ſhort when the Lord commeth. For he is ſpeedilie comming, and will take a ſtraight account of all you, that haue abuſed your ſtewardſhippes, and haue not bin faithfull in that was committed vnto you. He hath ſounded his Trompet now this ſecond time, and hath giuen you a lawfull warning, he hath tolde you often before, and he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7396:32"/>you now againe at the laſt, that you heape not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelues treaſure vpon the earth, where the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and ruſt do corrupt, &amp; theeues breake in &amp; ſteale, That if riches increaſe, you ſhould not ſet your heart vpon them,<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.</note> That riches helpe not in the day of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and he which truſteth in them ſhall haue a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible fall. That though ye thinke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> that your dwelling places ſhall continue for euer, yet ye ſhall dye and leaue your riches to others, That becauſe thou haſt truſted in thine owne treaſure, therefore thou and thy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Prieſtes ſhall be carried into captiuitie, That he which ſtoppeth his eare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the crye of the poore,<note place="margin">Prou. 21.</note> he ſhall crye himſelfe and not bee heard, That the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfulnes of riches, choketh vp the word of GOD,<note place="margin">I am. 5.</note> and maketh it vnfruitfull,<note place="margin">1. Timot. 6.</note> That we ſhould not truſt in the vncertaintie of riches,<note place="margin">Pſal 112.</note> but in the true and liuing God, That he which diſperſeth his goods, and giueth to the poore, his righteouſneſſe ſhall remaine for euer, That bleſſed are the rich which be found without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, and haue not put any truſt in monie and riches. And a thouſand ſuch other profitable warnings and promiſes hath he giuen you. But ye haue hardned your hearts, and thinke that ye ſhall neuer come to an account, how ye haue beſtowed them. Werefore the Canker and ruſt of them; yea the vayne and friuolous beſtowing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without profite to your neighbour, or benefite to the Church or Common weale, ſhall be a witnes againſt you at the day of Iudgement. Yea the ſupreme Iudge himſelfe, all the holie Angells &amp; elect of God, ſhall teſtifie againſt you: nay, your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb facs="tcp:7396:33"/>ſhall accuſe you, when you ſee before your eyes thoſe whom ye deſpiſed and oppreſſed; And the Lord himſelfe in that daie, ſhall ſaie vnto you: you are they vpon whom I beſtowed ſo many benefites, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I might haue giuen them vnto others farre more worthie then you: I made you ſtewards of my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, to diſpoſe them as might bee moſt agreeable to mine owne honor, for the reliefe of your poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which are members of my bodie, whome ye ſometime derided and ieſted at, and thought their life to be but madnes,<note place="margin">Wiſ. 5.</note> and their end to be without honor: But now ye ſee, that I haue choſen them before you, and made them heires of my ſaluation. You in this life had aboundance of all good things, but becauſe ye vſed not thoſe things as I had commaunded you, but abuſed them to your owne luſtes, I teſtifie againſt you, that the poore which before time indured al the penurie and miſerie of this life, ſhall now poſſeſſe the inheritance of my kingdome, and ye ſhall bee turned out. They, in ſtead of the cold, hunger, nakedneſſe, and trouble, which they ſuffered vpon the earth, ſhall now inioy all honor, glorie, pleaſure, and felicitie for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: But ye which exalted your ſelues in the pride of your riches, and dreamed of no other happines, but temporall honors and treaſures of the earth, ye ſhall now from henceforth feele nothing but euerlaſting paines, and griefes in hell, and bee tormented with the deuill and his Angels. Ye ſee the poore continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie before you in the ſtreates, the maymed and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable go from doore to doore, the impotent Lazars lye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7396:33"/>at your gates, the poore farherleſſe children and wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in continuall want. They deſire but the ſcraps that fall from your table, you ſhut you cares againſt them, and in the diſtreſſe of their ſoule they crie vnto God: and ſhall not God deliuer them in the time of their trouble, and call you to an account for them in the day of Iudgement? O vnkinde and vngratefull nature of man, beyond all the creatures that God hath made! The birdes of the aire that be lame or olde, or not able to ſeeke foode, are fed by the labour of other birds: The wilde beaſts that be ſicke and impotent to take anie pray of themſelues, are fedde by the pray of others; But ſhal men ſo degenerate from their own nature, and from the kind and nature of al other beaſts of the fielde, that hauing ouer and aboue that which ſhould ſuſteine themſelues and their familie, they wil not feede the hungrie, nor cloath the naked, nor helpe the maymed and impotent. Wherefore thoſe beaſts and foules of the aire ſhal riſe in the day of iudgement againſt them; nay al the creatures of God that are obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto man, &amp; ſerue for his life and ſuſtenaunce, ſhalbe a witneſſe againſt them in that woful &amp; dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall thoſe rich, whether they bee men or women, eſcape the iudgement of God; which gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to themſelues abundance of treaſure, deferre all their good deeds til the time of their death, &amp; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine then to diſpoſe all things after a good and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable manner: ſeeing for the moſt part, either their life is ſo dainlie taken from them before they haue ſet
<pb facs="tcp:7396:34"/>all in order; Or while they liue, they are ſpoyled of that they haue; Or elſe ſome other miſchaunce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth after their death, that things cannot be diſpoſed according to their will: But eſpeciallie, ſince in the meane time, they haue ſuffred manie Chriſtian ſoules to periſh for lacke of their helpe. Againe, what thanke is it to them to be liberal then, when they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie leaue their riches vnto others, and cannot vſe the ſame anie more themſelues.</p>
            <p>Neither wil the Iudge in that day, ſo ſtraightlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how they beſtowed the riches which they had at their death, as he will examine whether they did the workes of charitie in their life: Namelie; Whether they had pitie on the fatherles children, &amp; widowes, when they cried vnto them; Whether they helped the lame, and blinde, and impotent, that were not able to ſhifte for themſelues; Whether they gaue fuel and clothes to them that were cold and naked; Whether they releeued poore priſoners, when the yron entered into their ſoules; Whether they gaue Phiſicke to the ſicke, and ſurgerie the wounded; Whether they lent their monie freelie without hope of gaine; Whether they eaſed the common burden of the poore in time of famine: Whether they helped their Countrie and Common weale in time of neceſsitie; Whether they miniſtred vnto the Saintes in their aduerſitie; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they put their helping hand to the vpholding of Religion: And finallie, Whether they did all theſe things with a ſingle eye, and faithfull heart, not to be ſeene of men, but for pure loue to Chriſt &amp; his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7396:34"/>And then if they haue anie thing lefte at their death to be ſpared from their owne familie, let them beſtow the ſame in ſuch wiſe as may moſt tend to the glorie of God, to the edifieng of the Church, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the Common weale: And God ſhall reſtore them a thouſand folde in the life to come. But if they ſawe all thoſe neceſsities of their brethren, and did ſhut vp their compaſsion from them, and thought all too little for themſelues while they liued; all the good deedes at their death ſhall not be imputed one iot vnto them, but they ſhal haue their po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hipocrites, where ſhalbe weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: <hi>For they that haue ſhewed no mercie vnto others, ſhall haue iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without mercie to them ſelues:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Generallie, there is no eſtate nor degree of perſon whatſoeuer in this life, that ſhal eſcape fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but all ſhall appeare before the ſeate of GOD, and they that haue not walked with an vpright and ſincere heart before him, nor haue beleeued effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, nor liued fruitefullie in Ieſus Chriſt, wherby their ſinnes might not be imputed to them, ſhall aunſwere before him, not onelie for all the actuall ſinnes that they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt God, againſt their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, and againſt their owne ſoules, but they ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yeelde an account for euerie idle and vaine worde, that they haue ſpent all the time of their life, and ſo to receaue iudgement for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus are all mortall men and women cyted to appeare before the Iudgement ſeate of God to
<pb facs="tcp:7396:35"/>aunſwere for themſelues. There ſhall then be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of perſons before him: but Emperors, Kings, and Princes, their ſubiects, ſeruaunts, and vaſſals, all, both Magiſtrates and people, the higheſt Prelates and pooreſt Miniſters, Lords and tenants, maſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, parents and children, olde and young, one with another ſhall all ſtand before the face of the Lorde to receiue their iudgement; and either for their vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe to be accuſed and condemned, or elſe hauing walked with a perfect heart before him, they ſhalbee iuſtified and ſaued by the death and redemption of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeing al theſe things ſhall thus happen, &amp; that ſhortly, &amp; how ſodainly we know not: and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day of the Lord wil ſteale vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs like a theefe in the night,<note place="margin">2. Pet 3.</note> when the hauens ſhall paſſe away, and the earth and al the workes therein ſhalbe vtterly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with fire: ſeeing we ſhall immediately be caried away vnto iudgement, and ſeeing the Lord is not ſlacke, but will ſpeedelie come as he hath promiſed, what manner of perſons ought we to be in holineſſe and godly conuerſation? How ought we to purge our liues from the dead and damnable workes of this world to ſerue the true and liuing God? Howe well furniſhed ought we to be at all houres with all the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God, that nothing but truth may proceede out of our mouths: That all our actions bee defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by iuſtice and vpright dealing: That wee may treade all our ſteppes in the Goſpell of peace;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7396:35"/>That we may haue a ſtrong faith to withſtand the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and all the temptations of this life; That wee relie whollie vppon the ſaluation of Chriſt; and that the word of God may dwell plentifully in vs; wherewith we being indued, we ſhall be readie at euery inſtant to meete the Lord when he commeth in the clowdes with power and great glorie. But what ſhall the Lord ſay to them that bee ſo careleſſe and negligent as they will not watch one ſmall time in praier and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his comming? Shall they not in that great day be accuſed of the greateſt vnfaithfulnes in the world? Yea, ſhall they not bee condemned of foule and beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ingratitude; when for the pure loue that he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to vs, he hath ſo ſenſiblie before hand ſhewed vs of all theſe things that haue happened, and hath wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs to watch and bee readie with our Lampes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe the Sonne of man will come at ſuch an houre as we knowe not? O vngratefull and faithleſſe generation, maie he ſaie, it repenteth me that I haue been ſo kinde and louing to you, and that I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon you ſo large and ample benefites, when ye were dead in the burthen of your ſinnes, and were in thraldome of the deuill, and of all your mortall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nernies, and had no other waie to be relieued but by me, I humbled my ſelfe from the throne of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and tooke your nature vpon me: I came not as I might haue done, like a great Prince and Monarch of this world, but was content to abaſe my ſelfe to be borne of a poore woman, to bee brought vp like a poore childe, to walke in the forme of a poore ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant,
<pb facs="tcp:7396:36"/>and to liue poorely from the daie of my birth to the daie of my death. I indured nakedneſſe, and cold, and hunger for your ſakes, yea thirtie yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and vpward did I abide all the calamities of this life for your ſakes, I ſubmitted my ſelfe to the lawe of man, and obſerued euerie iot and title of the ſame for your ſakes, I faſted fourtie daies and fourtie nights for your ſakes, I wrought great miracles and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the world for your ſakes: And when the time of my paſsion was come, I ſweate water and bloud for your ſakes, I was ſcourged, buffetted, and beaten for your ſakes, I abode a crowne of ſharpe thornes vpon my head for your ſakes, I indured ſpitting, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and deſpightfull words againſt my ſelfe for your ſakes: And in the ende I ſuffered amoſt ſhamefull and cruell death vppon the Croſſe for your ſakes. For you and your ſaluation haue I done all this, and yet ye will not beleeue the ſignes that I haue ſhewed, nor prepare your ſelues to watch for my comming. Therefore I will come ſo ſodainlie vppon you, as it ſhall be too late for you to repent; and whome I finde not watching and prepared for me, him will I caſt into the vttermoſt darkenes, where ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my deare brethren in Chriſt, when we haue diligentlie weighed and conſidered theſe things; how iuſtlie, how innocentlie, and how purelie ought wee to ſhewe our ſelues in all the whole courſe of our liues, looking daylie and hourelie for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of our Sauiour, that we maie be blameleſſe in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7396:36"/>the daie of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. It is for our learning &amp; edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that al the holie Scriptures are written, that all the teaching, inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; warnings therin are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that all the miracles of God from the beginning haue been ſhewed, that all the examples of our forefathers haue been publiſhed, that God from the beginning was ſo mindfull of our redemption, &amp; that he ſent his owne Sonne for our ſaluation. It is we that he hath been ſo carefull to preſerue ſo many ages together, in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of ſo many crooked and peruerſe nations, &amp; from the hands of ſo many cruell &amp; bloudie tyrants. Who were preſerued in the Arke from the firſt deſtruction of the world by waters, but we? Who were ſaued from death in the great famine of <hi>Egipt</hi> and countries adioyning, but we? Who were deliuered from <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao,</hi> from the inhabitants of <hi>Chanaan,</hi> and from manie other nations with a mightie and ſtretched out arme, but we? Who were preſerued in the great and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible perſecutions of the Primitiue Church, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vtterly conſumed of tyrants, but we? Who were ſafelie kept by God as the apple of his owne eye, in ſo great and generall Apoſtacie of the Church, but we? Who were againe deliuered by God from the power of Antichriſt, and were indued with the knowledge of his truth, but we? Nay, who haue receiued ſo many tokens of the end of the world, &amp; warnings of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes comming, as we? For the heathen haue no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his lawes, And they that bee ſtraungers from Chriſt, feare not his iudgements, And all they which ſinned without law, ſhall periſh without law. Againe,
<pb facs="tcp:7396:37"/>if iudgement begin firſt with the houſe of God, what ſhall become of them that beleeue not the Goſpell?</p>
            <p>Why do not wee then with all faithfulneſſe and willng heart receiue all theſe Oracles ſent vs by God? Why doe wee not thankfully accept his benefites? Why do we not beleeue his promiſes? Why do wee not prepare our ſelues for his iudgements? Why doe we not weepe and bewaile and lament for our ſinnes? Why are we ſo ſtonie and hard hearted, that there is No example of temporall puniſhments in other, no feele of Gods wrath in our ſelues, no threatning of Gods vengance to come, no remembrance of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments paſt, no remorſe of conſcience for our ſinnes, no promiſe of temporall bleſsings, no aſſurance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall rewards: neither ſignes in heauen aboue, nor tokens in the earth beneath, nor the hope of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor feare of perpetuall damnation, that can once effectually moue vs to amend our liues, and make vs to forſake the ſinne that reigneth in our mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodies; although we know die kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to be neuer ſo neere, nay, euen at the very doore. Wherefore I feare me it will be pronounced againſt vs, that was ſometime againſt the vnbeleeuing cities of <hi>Iuda.</hi> Woe be vnto you Chriſtians, and eſpeciallie you that haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon you to reforme my Church, and to haue my Goſpell preached among you, woe I ſay bee vnto you: For if the ſignes and myracles that haue bin in your time, and among you, had bin done among the Turkes and Infidels, yea among the moſt ſauadge Indians of the world, they would long ſince
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7396:37"/>haue repented inſackecloth and aſhes! O that wee would open the fountaines of our heart, and powre in contrition into our ſoule! O that wee had a floud of teares to bewaile the multitude of our ſinnes! O that we would haue but ſome parte of that affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our ſelues, that the creatures of God haue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs! For they mourne and lament for our ſins, they long for our deliuerance becauſe of our ſinnes; The earth trembleth &amp; quaketh becauſe of our ſinns; The Sonne and the Moone want of their light and beautie, for our ſinnes, The Heauens powre downe floudes of deſtruction for our ſinnes; The plants and hearbes lacke their vertue and operation, for our ſinnes: The windes goe foorth of their places, &amp; the ſeaſons of the yere keepe not their wonted courſe, for our ſinnes: yea, the natures of all creatures are in a manner changed for our ſinnes. But what ſhall I ſaye more? The Angels of God doe mourne for our ſins: The verie ſoules of the righteous doe lament for our ſinnes: And it greeueth the ſpirite of God himſelfe, that we perſiſt in our ſinnes: But all this mooueth not our ſenſes, nor yet melteth our owne heartes for our ſinnes:</p>
            <p>All that we ſpeake, all that we write, all the labor we take, is in vaine: For our heart is as hard as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant, and our ſoule refuſeth counſell. Euerie man ſpeaketh of the mercies of GOD; Euerie man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth his benefits? Euerie man hath the word of God in his lippes; Euerie man crieth <hi>Lorde, Lord;</hi> but no man dooth the will of his heauenlie Father;
<pb facs="tcp:7396:38"/>Euerie man confeſſeth the tokens of Chriſt to bee come, but no man prepareth him ſelfe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: No man maketh attonement with his brother, no man ſheweth the fruites of faith, no man forſaketh his wicked life, no man keepeth his veſſell pure and holie to the Lorde. Euerie man blameth, euerie man reprooueth, euerie man condemneth ſhamefull actes in others, but no man amendeth anie one ſinne in himſelfe. O gracious GOD, why ſhoulde thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thus forget thee? why ſhoulde they bee thus ſtiff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necked againſt thee? why ſhoulde they ſo deepelie diſſembled with thee? why ſhoulde they make as though they beleeued thy worde, when they bee ſo farre from reforming of their liues? why ſhould they be ſo rauiſhed with earthlie delightes, that periſh in a moment, and contemne the hauenlie ioyes, which continue for euer? why ſhoulde they bee thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraught from the ſenſe and feele of hapineſſe, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the delightes and pleaſures of their owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? Shal the care of tranſitorie riches of this world, drowne the deſire of glorie in the worlde to come? Shall the vglie and deceaueable luſtes of ſinne, that breede long and bitter repentaunce, preuaile aboue the beautifull contemplation of thine eternall God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? Shall this vale of miſerie, (wherein wee ſee nothing but ſinne and wickedneſſe, nothing but care and vexation of minde, nothing but perilles by lande and ſea, at home and abroade, in bedde and at boord, in freedome and in bondage, in pouertie &amp; in welth,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7396:38"/>in honour and diſgrace, at all times, and in all places, both in life and in death) bee more deepelie printed in our heart, than the Kingdome of Chriſt; wherein the bodie ſhall bee chaunged from corruption to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, from diſhonour to glorie, from weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſtrength, from a naturall bodie to a ſpirituall bodie; wherein all paines and ſorrowes ſhall bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vaniſhed, and all quietneſſe and tranquilitie of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall dwell for euermore? Nay, ſhall the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection which wee beare to father, or mother, or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ſiſter, or wife, or children, or landes, or goods, or to haue die whole earth at our becke and commaundement, once ſeperate vs from the loue that is in Chriſt Ieſus; from the companie that wee ſhall haue with his holie Angells, from the fellowſhip of all the godlie and elect people, and from the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fruition of Gods diuine preſence and Maieſtie? GOD forbid.</p>
            <p>What is the cauſe then that wee ſo greedelie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and laye holde vpon theſe tranſitorie thinges? Nothing verelie, but the corruption of our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the following of our owne ſenſuall pleaſures, and the inſtigation of the diuell; who laboureth now towardes the ende of the worlde more ſtronglie than euer, to drawe all the ſoules that he can into damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with himſelfe; of whom we, to our great ſhame, ſtande in ſeare, as though Chriſt our Conqueror had neuer redeemed vs, as though he that had once ſaued vs, could no more defende vs.</p>
            <p>But alas, why ſhoulde wee not continuallie and
<pb facs="tcp:7396:39"/>vnfainedlie praye vnto God to aſsiſt vs, and with the ſtrength of his holie ſpirite to defende vs from all our wicked enemies, that in him, &amp; by him we may haue grace to vanquiſh and ouercome, whenſoeuer we are preſſed or diſquieted either in bodie or minde.</p>
            <p>But as concerning ſinne, albeit wee for our owne parts haue made ſuch a couenant with death, as what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer be ſaid vnto vs we will not amend: &amp; haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into ſuch a league with hell, that we will not be ſaued: albeit we haue refuſed the mercie of God, that calleth all men to repentance, and would all men to be ſaued; yet after we haue once receaued the knowledge of the truth, and haue been baptized in the name of Chriſt, and haue promiſed to liue in his true faith and feare, let vs neuer ſo treade vnder foote the Sonne of God; nor worke ſuch deſpite vnto the ſpirit of grace, that through our vngodlie and ſinfull life, we ſhoulde make the Gentiles to hate the name of Chriſt for our ſakes, and by this meanes to keepe both out ſelues and others too out of the kingdome of Chriſt. Which otherwiſe, if they ſaw our iuſt and ſincere conuerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwerable to the forme of our profeſsion, they would ioyne them ſelues vnto the bodie of Chriſt, &amp; ſo magnifie his name ouer all the world.</p>
            <p>Shall not the zeale of our forefathers, who in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of vs that haue the light of the Goſpell, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued but in darkeneſſe and in the ſhadowe of death, be a notable teſtimony againſt vs in the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; ſince they feared god more reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, ſerued him more willingly, obeyed him more dutifully, and loued him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7396:39"/>more feruently the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we? Since they had more compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton vpon their pore brethren, more deuotion vnto al good workes, and more regard to their owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then we? Since they had leſſe diſsimulation, leſſe craft, leſſe hypocriſie, leſſe malice, leſſe couetouſneſſe, leſſ wickedneſſ in their life then we?</p>
            <p>Compare the great zeale of our predeceſſors, with the colde deuotion that wee haue in theſe daies; and we ſhall be aſhamed of our ſelues. The good deedes which were done by them, were done ſimplie, either for the loue they bare to God, or (as they tooke it) for the honor of his ſeruice and religion, or of a compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to their poore brethren, or for the ſafetie of their owne ſoules, or of a zeale they bare to their parents departed, or for a benefite to the Common wealth, or to eaſe the burthen of their ſucceſſors, or for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Schooles and learning, or for ſome ſuch other, either good or wel-meaning intent. But on the other ſide, what little good ſoeuer we doe, we doe it, neither of a lone towards GOD, nor of a charitable minde towards our neighbour, nor of any remorſe of conſcience in our ſelues, nor yet of any affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our natiue countrie; but all that the moſt of vs do, we do it either for vaine glorie, or for pleaſing of other mens humours, or to bee ſeene and praiſed of men, or to auoyd the clamor of the world, or by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion and commandement, or for feare of ſhame and puniſhment, or by importunate ſute that is made, or becauſe wee knowe not els what to do with that we haue. Wherefore, the former with their blind zeale
<pb facs="tcp:7396:40"/>and ſuppoſed good intent, ſhall riſe vp in the daie of iudgement and condemne vs for the fruitleſſe oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and boaſting of our faith. If the men of <hi>Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie</hi> which repented at the preaching of <hi>Ionas,</hi> and the Queene of the <hi>South,</hi> that came ſo farre to heare the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſhall riſe in iudgement againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that would not beleeue and amend, for all that could bee ſaid vnto them by Chriſt and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. What ſhall ſo manie Prophets and Preachers of God do againſt vs in that day, who daily &amp; houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and continuallie rebuke vs for our ſinnes, and ſtirre vs vp by all meanes to amendment of our liues, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs that the daie of the Lord is at hand.</p>
            <p>O Ieſus, why ſhould we now be further from the obeying of thee, than when wee were further from thee? Shall the brightnes of thy preſence, and the light of thy bleſſed word which lighteneth euerie man that commeth into the world, and whoſe propertie is to giue light and ſaluation to all them that will receiue the ſame, ſhall it ſhine (I ſaie) vppon ſuch ſtonie and grauelie hearts, as haue no power to bring forth true repentance, nor any fruites of a godlie life? And ſhall the Deuill ſo preuaile againſt them, for whom thou haſt ſhed thy moſt precious bloud, that ſodainlie (vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the reuealing of Antichriſt, and ſending of new Ambaſſadours from thee, to put thinges in order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy comming) he ſhall turne the hearts of all men from all goodneſſe and vertue, to vice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie; alter the natures of things from better to worſe; bring in Schiſme, Atheiſme, Treaſon, and all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7396:40"/>into the worlde, and make iniquitie flowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure ouer all the bankes of the earth? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, Lorde if this bee thy will, and that by no other meanes thy holie word ſhould bee verified, namelie, that wickedneſſe ſhould ſo mightilie abound before thy comming: If thy promiſe ſhould on this wiſe bee fulfilled: If thy choſen muſt on this manner bee tried; and that this ſhould bee one of the laſt tokens of thy comming; wee accept all theſe things as Oracles ſent before, and wee aſſuredlie looke for thine owne ſelfe in perſon to followe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ye my brethren of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, for whoſe cauſe ſpecially I haue written this ſecond warning, or ſound of the laſt Trompet, beare in minde all theſe thinges that I haue declared vnto you: Examine your owne conſciences, whether ye haue not taſted of the bleſsings of GOD, in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure more aboundantlie, in fauour more apparantlie, in mercie more infinitlie, and in ſignes and tokens more wonderfullie, than anie nation in the world. Againe, conſider with your ſelues, how all theſe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and mercies haue been requited of you. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there bee anie nation of the worlde more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull for Gods benefites, more forgetfull of his promiſes, more diſobedient to his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, more negligent in their callings, more factious in practiſes, more contentious in Religion, more inclined to Treaſon, more vncharitable in action, more colde in deuotion, more raſh in enterpriſes, more reſtleſſe in vanities, more greedie in getting,
<pb facs="tcp:7396:41"/>more careleſſe in ſpending, more ſlowe to vertue and more forward to vice: And finally, more deſperate to all kinde of miſchiefe, then commonly the people of this kingdome are. Wherefore, if the mercies of God did not daylie ſalue the deadly wounds and diſeaſes of our ſoule, wee ſhould long before this time haue come to a feareful and horrible end. But that the Lord doth yet ſpare you, impute it not to your owne deſert, but to his great mercy. That ye periſh &amp; conſume not in his wrath, it is of his mercie: That ye liue vnpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued of your enemies, is of his mercie: That ye looſe not his Goſpell and true Religion, is of his mercie: That we ſee our <hi>Elizabeth</hi> reigne in holineſſe, health, and proſperitie, is long of his mercie: And yet for all this do we reiect his goodneſſe, diſcredite his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, diſhonor his ſeruices, diſallowe his tokens, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſinnes, deuide the Church with Schiſmes, and ſlaunder the trueth of the Goſpell by our vngodlines: yet for all this do ye crye, Peace, Peace, and think that all ſhall go aſwell with you at the laſt, as it did at the firſt: And conſider not the mercifull patience and long ſuffring of the Lord, &amp; how he calleth you to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For ye ſhall al dye with euerlaſting deſtruction, vnleſſe ye ſpeedily ſhewe foorth the fruites of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And the patient forbearing of temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of your bodies in this life, doth breede the greater weight of perpetuall ſhame and damnation both of bodie and ſoule in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Farre more eaſie ſhould it bee for vs, if our ſinnes had not deſerued greater puniſhement, that it would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7396:41"/>pleaſe the Lord fatherlie to correct vs while wee are heere, either with publicke warres, plagues and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines; or elſe with priuate ſickneſſe, penurie, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, and with loſſe of goods and poſſeſsions: if he would feede vs with the bread of teares, and with the water of affliction; if he would exerciſe vs with all kinde of miſerie, and ſo purge and trie vs as it were by fire; yea, if he would humble vs as he did <hi>Nabuca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor,</hi> and make vs to eate graſſe with the beaſtes of the field, and to water vs with the deaw of heauen, till our hearts were whollie turned vnto him againe: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than do fill vs ſo abundantlie with all manner of temporal bleſsings: With health in our bodies, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in our coffers, ioy in our families, fauour with our Princes; to haue praiſe with priuate perſons, and to haue authoritie in kingdomes: but therewith to bee depriued of the grace and mercie of God, of Chriſtes promiſed ſaluation, and in ſteede of the pleaſures of this life, to receaue paines intollerable both of bodie and ſoule in the life to come.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ô my bretheren remember what yee are, where yee are, and whether yee goe. Yee are of thoſe, for whom the world was made; For whome the remnant was ſaued in <hi>Noahs</hi> floud; For whome God hath ſhewed a thouſand miracles in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> in the redde Sea, and in the wilderneſſe; For whome Chriſt liued ſo manie yeeres in this wretched world; and for whome hee ſuffered ſo ſhamefull death vpon the Croſſe: Yee are the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the bleſſed: Yee are of the Church, and
<pb facs="tcp:7396:42"/>members of Chriſtes bodie: Yee are the veſſells of the holie Ghoſt, if yee liue holilie and vnblameablie: And ye are of them, to whom the promiſe of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life was made.</p>
            <p>Remember alſo, that yee are in this tranſitorie world, a place ſo latelie made, &amp; which ſhall ſo ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie periſh; wherein there is nothing but luſtes of the freſh, luſtes of the eyes, and pride of life. Remember that a thouſande yeeres with the Lorde are but as one day, and that all your whole life is not one hower of ſuch a day. Remember that yee are in a place full of miſeries, cares, and troubles, among a crooked and peruerſe generation, among a people that haue ſolde them ſelues to commit wickedneſſe, and that with all greedie deſire: That a mans dayes paſſe awaie like a ſhaddowe, and his yeeres like vanitie, That though he be the mightieſt Prince &amp; Monarch of the world, yet when age &amp; infirmities creepe vpon him, he deſireth to be loſed from the burthen of this fleſh.</p>
            <p>Againe remember the place whereunto yee ſhall tende: For yee are heere but pilgrimes and ſtraungers for a little ſeaſon; And as manie of you as are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, muſt home to your owne Countrey of Heauen; A place of libertie, a place of felicitie, a place of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting pleaſure; Where time ſhall be no more time; where night and darkeneſſe ſhall be baniſhed; where yee ſhall neither hunger nor thirſt; where yee ſhall neither luſt nor deſire; where it is vnpoſsible yee ſhoulde die anie more; where the Lorde him ſelfe ſhall bee your foode and portion, and the light of your
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7396:42"/>countenaunce; where the meaſure of your ioyes ſhall be full, and where ye ſhall liue in pleaſure and felicitie for euermore.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, as manie of you as are called Chriſtians, and are not of the flocke of Chriſt, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie as refuſe this ſaluation offered you, in not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing as you ought, and liuing as you ſhould, As ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of you as truſt not whollie to be ſaued by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Chriſt Ieſus, but iuſtifie your ſelues by your owne workes: Naie, all you that boaſt of your faith in Chriſt, and yet mortifie not your carnall members, nor walke in the ſteppes of his commaundements: As many as make Chriſt Ieſus but a ſtraunger to you, and ſeeke for other Mediatours than his owne ſelfe: As manie as frame vnto the Church a monſterous head vpon the earth, beſides our owne mercifull head Chriſt Ieſus in heauen: As manie as will make the decrees of mans corrupt iudgement, equall with the moſt holie and ſacred word of GOD: As manie as refuſe to laie holde on Chriſt by faith, and runne for helpe vnto Images and dumme Idolls: As manie as fruſtrate the benefites of Chriſtes death, by redeeming their ſinnes with monie and pardons: As manie as thinke to obtaine their requeſtes by a ſet number of verball prayers, without any earneſt meditation of the merite and promiſe of Chriſt: As manie as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane that glorious bodie of Chriſt Ieſus, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of any creature for and in the name of him, and ſo cut off the hand of faith, whereby we hold faſt by him as he ſitteth on the right hand of his Father:
<pb facs="tcp:7396:43"/>Briefly, as many as know that God muſt be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſpirit and trueth, and yet will cleaue to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh toyes and fooliſh ſuperſtitions of Antichriſt. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, as many as walke after their owne waies, and not as the Lord himſelfe hath commaunded in his holie worde: All theſe muſt likewiſe home to their countrie; a place of torment, a place of eternal trouble, a cruell and terrible habitation, continuallie to bee vexed with burning fire and moſt intollerable heate, mingled neuertheleſſe with palpable darknes; not for a time and ſeaſon, but perpetuallie and for euer there to remaine, vnder the dominion of <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his Angels, whoſe workes they followed, and whoſe commaundements they obeyed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore, if there yet remaine in you any ſparke of godlineſſe, anie loue of Religion, anie dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, anie hope of the reſurrection to come, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie deſire of ſaluation, anie feare of damnation: if all faith, all conſcience, all goodneſſe, and all religion be not quite extinguiſhed; reuiue your mindes, lifte vp your hearts, aſcend vnto Chriſt by faith; Set your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vpon things aboue, and not vpon thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath; Caſt away all vaine and idle cogitations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your liues, forſake your ſins, returne no more to your filthie pleaſures, giue ouer your ſuperfluous vanities, cleanſe your ſelues from all vngodlineſſe: &amp; as you haue hetherto giuen ouer your members to ſerue vncleanneſſe, ſo make them now to be ſeruants vnto righteouſneſſe. Crucifie the olde man in you, that the bodie of ſinne may be vtterly deſtroyed.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:7396:43"/>
            <p>Come out from Babylon, and be no more partaker of her wickedneſſe, touch no more vncleanneſſe, and the Lord will receiue you. Euery one of you abound in charitie one towards another, euen as Chriſt hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued you and hath giuen himſelfe for you. Be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſpirite of your minde, and put on the newe man, which is ſhapen in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe. Examine your ſelues whether you be in the faith: and knowe for certaintie that Chriſt is in you, except ye bee reprobates. Clenſe your hearts from all filthines and ſinne, and go forth to meet with the Bridegrome. So ſhall all your former ſinnes be wiped out of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Ye ſhalbe his people, and he wil be your God. He will ſeperate you from the wicked, and ſet you on his right hand. He will protect you in this life from al your enemies, and in the life to come, will giue you a kingdome of euerlaſting happineſſe: Come therfore Lord Ieſus, Come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, for the ſaluation of thy choſen, and gladnes of thy people.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
